[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The term plastic is derived from the term ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plasticos",
            "b) Plastikos",
            "c) Plastiquo",
            "d) Plastein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The term plastic is derived from the Greek word plastikos. The word “plastic” or “plastics” originated from the Greek word “plastikos”, which means – to form or grow.  The word plastic means the capability to be formed, which is one of the features of plastics.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "When was the first folding carton commercially used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1789",
            "b) 1850",
            "c) 1897",
            "d) 1880"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first folding carton was commercially used in 1897, by NABISCO (National Biscuit Company). They used it for packaging their product Uneeda Biscuit.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "What does the term plastikos mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easily shaped or deformed",
            "b) Stretchable",
            "c) Bendable",
            "d) Malleable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Greek term plastikos means easily shaped or deformed. It is a Greek term which originated from the Greek term plassein, which means – to mould.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first synthetic plastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PVC",
            "b) PP",
            "c) Bakelite",
            "d) Nylon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1907, Leo Baekeland, a Belgian chemist, invented Bakelite. Bakelite, also known as polyoxybenzylmethylenglycolanhydride, is the first synthetic polymer made from phenol and formaldehyde.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "When was retort pouch first developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1900s",
            "b) 1950s",
            "c) 1850s",
            "d) 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Retort pouch was first developed in 1950s. A retort pouch is a packaging material, composed of different layers – Polypropylene (food contact layer), Nylon (Abrasion Resistance layer), Aluminium foil (Barrier Layer) and Polyester (outside layer). In 1950s, the retort pouch for heat-processed foods was developed originally for the US military, to pack Ready to Eat food items.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first man-made plastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parkesine",
            "b) Nylon",
            "c) Teflon",
            "d) Polyvinyl Chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Parkesine, also known as nitrocellulose is the first man made plastic. It was made majorly from cellulose, treated with nitric acid as a solvent. It was made by Alexander Parkes in 1856.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Who is called the “father of canning”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peter Durand",
            "b) Bryan Donkin",
            "c) Nicholas Appert",
            "d) Robert Yeates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Nicholas Appert is known as the “father of canning”. He was a confectioner. In 1809, in France, Nicolas Appert produced the means of thermally preserving food in hermetically sealed glass jars.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "When was first commercial paperboard produced commercially?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1850",
            "b) 1817",
            "c) 1915",
            "d) 1945"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first commercial paperboard was produced in 1817, by the firm M. Treverton and Son. Paperboard is a packaging material, thicker than paper possessing characteristics like foldability and rigidity. Paper with grammage greater than 250 g/m2 is called paperboard.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Which of the following was used by Peter Durand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellophane",
            "b) Tin Cans",
            "c) Corrugated Fiberboard",
            "d) Glass jar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  In 1810, Peter Durand designed the soldered tinplate canister and commercialised the use of heat preserved food containers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "When was folding box first used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1805",
            "b) 1817",
            "c) 1845",
            "d) 1884"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The first folding box was used by Quaker Oats in 1884. Quaker oats is a company that mainly produces oatmeal and cereal products. In 1884, folding boxes were used to package rolled white oats.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "In which year was cellophane invented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1930",
            "b) 1990",
            "c) 1908",
            "d) 1900"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cellophane was first invented by Jacques E. Brandenberger, a Swiss textile engineer in 1908. It is a transparent film which is thin and quite stiff. It is a polymeric film  made from regenerated cellulose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "When was Nylon invented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1999",
            "b) 1985",
            "c) 1915",
            "d) 1935"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nylon, a synthetic polymer, was produced in 1935.  Nylon was developed by a research team at DuPont, headed by an American chemist, Wallace H. Carothers. It was made by the chemical synthesis of adipic acid and hexamethylrnrdiamine mainly, by condensation polymerisation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Who is the inventor of PET bottles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nicholas Appert",
            "b) Peter Durand",
            "c) Nathaniel Wyeth",
            "d) Bryan Donkin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pet bottle (also known as plastic soda bottle) was invented by Nathaniel Wyeth in 1973. PET is a kind of polyester, capable of holding carbonated beverages.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "When was the first pop top aluminium can produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1959",
            "b) 1999",
            "c) 1905",
            "d) 1950"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1959, also called “pull-tab”. Invented by Ermal Fraze. This eliminated the need for a separate opener tool by attaching an aluminium pull ring lever with a rivet to a scored wedge shaped tab section of can top.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "When was edible packaging introduced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000",
            "b) 2015",
            "c) 2012",
            "d) 2009"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Edible packaging, also called Food wrapped in food, was introduced in 2012. WikiFoods in 2012 along with Stonyfield introduced this novelty to market.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Polyethylene is a polymer of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) C2H4",
            "b) C4H6",
            "c) CH4",
            "d) C2H2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polyethylene (PE) is a polymer of Ethylene (C2H4). It’s IUPAC name is polyethene or  Poly(methylene). It was first synthesized by a German chemist Hans von Pechman in 1898.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Which of the following is called poison plastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PP",
            "b) PET",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) LDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PVC, Polyvinyl Chloride is called poison plastic. It releases many chemicals such as- dioxins, lead, ethylene dichloride, vinyl chloride, which is very harmful for health. High exposure to these chemicals causes diseases such as asthma and other respiratory ailments.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a step in Addition polymerization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propagation",
            "b) Condensation",
            "c) Termination",
            "d) Initiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Condensation is not a step in addition polymerization. Addition polymerization includes three steps, via- initiation, propagation and termination. Condensation polymerization is another kind of polymerization reaction, which includes- joining of two compounds by losing a small molecule (generally a water molecule).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Styrene is also called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethylbenzene",
            "b) Phenylphrene",
            "c) Methylbenzene",
            "d) Vinylpyridine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Condensation polymerization is called Step Growth Polymerization. Addition polymerization is called chain growth polymerization. Hence, the answer is false.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which of the following has greater density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polypropylene",
            "b) High Density Polyethlene",
            "c) Polystyrene",
            "d) Polyvinyl chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Styrene is also known as ethylbenzene. Its chemical formula is C6H5CH=CH2.  The polymerization of styrene via addition mechanism. It finds many uses in packaging industry due to some of its attributes like, clarity, hardness and brittleness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the strongest plastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Teflon",
            "b) High Density Polyethylene",
            "c) Polystyrene",
            "d) Polycarbonate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Amongst the given, PVC (Polyvinyl Chloride) has the greatest density. Density of Polypropylene is 0.946 g/cm3. Density of High Density Polyethlene is 0.970 g/cm3. Density of polystyrene ranges  from 0.96 – 1.04 g/cm3. Density of Polyvinyl chloride ranges from 1.3 – 1.45 g/cm3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which of the following is microwave safe plastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PET",
            "b) PVC",
            "c) PP",
            "d) PS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polycarbonate is the strongest plastic. It has properties such as high impact strength, high flexibility, durability – which make it very suitable for construction purposes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Which of the following plastics has identification number 6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PS",
            "b) HDPE",
            "c) LDPE",
            "d) PET"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polypropylene (PP) is microwave safe plastic. It is produced from addition polymerization of propylene. Its melting point is about 160°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for juice bottles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDPE",
            "b) PP",
            "c) PET",
            "d) PS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polystyrene (PS) has identification number 6. The identification number ranges from 1-7, plastics being, PET, HDPE, PVC, LDPE, PP, PS and others respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as imitation glassware?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PS",
            "b) PVC",
            "c) PET",
            "d) HDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HDPE (High Density Polyethylene) is used for making juice bottles. It is a thermoplastic polymer made by polymerization of ethylene. It has a high strength-to-density ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used in making carrier bags?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PP",
            "b) LDPE",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) PET"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polystyrene is used for manufacture of imitation glassware. It is a clear, hard and brittle polymer, making it suitable for making imitation glassware. It is also used as a container for yogurt and jelly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a plastic colorant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diarylide",
            "b) Tartrazine",
            "c) Sudan stain",
            "d) Oil blue A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tartrazine is not a plastic colorant. It is an artificial dye (Lemon yellow colored) used in foods. Sudan stain and Oil blue A are dyes and Diarylide is a pigment. Colorants are added to plastic to give it a desired colour.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "What is the function of biostabilizers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To regulate hardness",
            "b) Obtain better impact resistance",
            "c) Control surface tension",
            "d) To prevent deterioration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Biostabilizers helps to prevent deterioration of plastic. Biostabilizers are also called as antimicrobials because itdecreases susceptibility of plastic against microbial attack.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "What is the function of fillers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase conductance",
            "b) Reduce sinkage",
            "c) Increase stiffness and hardness",
            "d) Improve ability to absorb shock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fillers help in increasing the stiffness and hardness of a plastic. Substances like photoinitiators increase electrical stability. Impact modifiers improve the ability to absorb shock. Blowing agents reduces sinkage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a filler?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CaCo3",
            "b) SbO3",
            "c) Silica",
            "d) Asbestos"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Foaming agents are also known as blowing agents. They are used during the process of blow moulding, to reduce or eliminate sink marks. It gives a foam structure to the plastic, hence the name foaming agent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a lubricant used in plastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicone oil",
            "b) Low mol wt PE",
            "c) Neoprene",
            "d) Halogens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Antimony Trioxide (SbO3) is not filler. Rest of these are fillers used in plastics. Fillers provide rigidity to the plastic, thereby increasing its tensile strength and toughness. It also increases elastic modulus and wear resistance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "What is the function of plasticizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improve rheology",
            "b) Lower glass transition temperature",
            "c) Increase electrical stability",
            "d) Improve strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Halogens are not lubricants; they are flame retarders. Silicone oil, low molecular weight polyethylene and neoprene are lubricants.  Lubricants are used to prevent any damage caused to plastic during its processing (especially the moulding process).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a UV light absorber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phosphate esters",
            "b) Quaternary ammonium compounds",
            "c) Polyethylene glycol esters",
            "d) Benzophenones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: UV stabilizers are added to plastics to increase the life of plastics, especially when exposed to UV lights. The following UV stabilizers are generally used- benzotriazoles, alkylated hindered phenol, benzophenones, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Halogens are used as _______ in plastics.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flame retardant",
            "b) UV light absorber",
            "c) Antimicrobial",
            "d) Antistatic agents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Anti-oxidants are used in plastic to prevent oxidation. Plastics deteriorate due to oxidation – unstable melt flow properties, brittleness, discoloration and loss of tensile properties. Following are the commonly used anti-oxidants used in plastics-arylamines, phenols, phosphites and various sulfur compounds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Adipate diesters are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flame retardant",
            "b) Antimicrobial",
            "c) UV light absorber",
            "d) Plasticizers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Plasticizers lower the glass transition temperature of plastics. Therefore, it helps to make the plastic more flexible. It does so by decreasing its viscosity in a way. Rheology is improved by lubricants. Substances like photoinitiators increase electrical stability and fillers improve strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which amongst the following is not a food grade polymer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethylene Propylene Diene monomer",
            "b) Polyurethane",
            "c) Polyvinyl Chloride",
            "d) Viton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polyvinyl Chloride (PVC) is not a food grade polymer. It is toxic in nature.  A polymer is a labeled food grade when it is inert and doesn’t react with food in a harmful manner. Ethylene propylene diene monomer, polyurethane and viton are food grade polymers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a mechanism of film formation in edible coating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple co-acervation",
            "b) Complex co-acervation",
            "c) Polymerisation",
            "d) Gelation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Edible packaging material is more sustainable than traditional packaging material. It is because of its biodegradable property. Traditional packaging material leaves residues on degrading, whereas edible packaging does not. Therefore, making it more sustainable and suitable for the environment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "____________ and ___________ are used to make edible packaging material.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minerals and vitamins",
            "b) Proteins and vitamins",
            "c) Water and proteins",
            "d) Proteins and carbohydrates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polymerisation is not a mechanism of film formation in edible coating. Simple co-acervation, compound co-acervation and gelation are mechanisms of film formation in edible coating. Polymerisation is a phenomenon when monomers combine together to form a polymer. Film formation mechanisms are those which tell about the interaction of film and the substrate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "_________ is a protein based material for edible coating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chitosan",
            "b) Acylglycerol",
            "c) Collagen",
            "d) Alginate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Proteins and carbohydrates are used to make edible packaging material. The protein based material includes-gluten, zein, soy,etc. Carbohydrates based material includes-chitosan, cellulose, dextrin, pectin,etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Gelation is a ________ of formation of edible coating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Consequence",
            "b) Mechanism",
            "c) Result",
            "d) Prerequisite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Collagen is a protein based material for edible coating. Chitosan and alginate are polymer based material for edible coating. Acylglycerol is a lipid based material for edible coating.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Cohesive forces between ___________ is a principal of film formation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inner membrane and cell wall",
            "b) Film and substrate",
            "c) Endocarp and mesocarp",
            "d) Polymer molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Simple co-acervation includes addition of hydrosoluble non-electrolyte. Complex co-acervation is simple precipitation of polymer complex, when two hydrocolloids of opposite charges are mixed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Adhesive forces between _______________ is a principal of film formation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polymer molecules",
            "b) Inner membrane and cell wall",
            "c) Film and substrate",
            "d) Endocarp and mesocarp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gelation is a mechanism of formation of edible coating. Gelation is a process when the heating of polymers leads to its denaturation, followed by gelation or coagulation on cooling. Gelation is also known as thermal coagulation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Which of the following properties make edible/biodegradable packaging material better than the traditional packaging material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compostability",
            "b) Water vapor transmission rate",
            "c) Oxygen transmission rate",
            "d) Thermal properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Biobased polymers are generally hydrophilic in nature. So are many traditional polymers like nylon, ethylvinyl alcohol, etc. Permeability may increase when humidity increases in both cases. Hence, we can say that edible packaging has comparable water vapor transmission rates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is false about edible/biobased packaging material when compared to traditional packaging material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improved product flavor",
            "b) Resistance to oxygen permeability",
            "c) Low water vapor permeability",
            "d) More sustainable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cohesive forces between polymer molecules are a principle of film formation. It is responsible for the barrier properties of the film. It helps in decreasing the permeability and hence transmission rates of gases and water respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "Chitosan, a polymer based material for edible coating, also has _______ properties.",
        "Options": [
            "a) antifungal",
            "b) antioxidant",
            "c) antifogging",
            "d) thickening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adhesive forces between film and substrate are a principle of film formation. It is responsible for keeping the film intact. This forms an edible film, which can be consumed along with the food.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "What does PHB stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyhydrobutyl",
            "b) Polyhydroxybutyrate",
            "c) Polyhydroxybutene",
            "d) Polyhydroxybutane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compostability makes edible/biodegradable packaging material better than the traditional packaging material. Compostability is also known as biodegradability. It is the property when the package meets its end life, how well a material decomposes. Biodegradable packets degrades faster and better than the traditional polymers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "CEN headquarters are located in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brussels",
            "b) London",
            "c) New York",
            "d) Rome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Edible / biobased packaging material has a higher water vapor permeability than traditional packaging material. However it is better than traditional packaging material since it helps improving product flavor, has a higher resistance to oxygen permeability and is more sustainable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which of the following optical properties cannot be measured by spectrophotometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gloss",
            "b) Haze",
            "c) Optical Distortion",
            "d) Yellowness Index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gloss cannot be measured by spectrophotometer. It is measured by a glossmeter. Gloss is an inherent property of any material. It is a measure of light reflected by the surface of a material. Rest of the optical properties is measured by spectrophotometer. Haze is produced by scattering of light when passed through a material. Optical Distort is the ability to distort light. Yellowness Index is the parameter to check the deviation of color of the material towards yellow or white.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is used for Grease Resistance Testing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quinone",
            "b) Azo dye",
            "c) Sudan Dye",
            "d) Malachite green"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For plastics, Grease resistance can be performed directly in pouches using groundnut oil colored with Sudan dye. Grease resistance is conducted to measure the resistance of a plastic towards grease, by exposing it to grease containing dye and measuring the time it takes to show at the unexposed side.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "What is the correct order of their tensile strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PSU < PC < PVC < PS",
            "b) PC < PSU < PS < PVC",
            "c) PC < PS < PSU < PVC",
            "d) PVC < PS < PC < PSU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct order of tensile strength of given plastics is – PVC<PS<PC<PSU. The tensile of the mentioned plastics is – Polyvinyl Chloride:40-50 N/mm2, Polystyrene:50-65 N/mm2, Polycarbonate:65-70 N/mm2, Polysulfone:70-80 N/mm2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Arrange the following in correct order of modulus of elasticity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PVC < Teflon < PET < Polyimide",
            "b) Polyimide < PET < Teflon < PVC",
            "c) PVC < PET < Teflon < Polyimide",
            "d) Polyimide < Teflon < PET < PVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement is false. Thermoplastics do not have crosslinking of monomers. Because of the absence of this chemical reaction, the processing cycles are comparatively short. Thermoplastics are made by linear chain polymerization of monomers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Which of the following thermoplastics is transparent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyphenylene Sulfide (PPS)",
            "b) Polystyrene (PS)",
            "c) Polyaryletheretherketone(PEEK)",
            "d) Polypropylene (PP)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Modulus of elasticity is a term which measures a substance’s resistance to being deformed when a stress is applied on it. The modulus of elasticity is in the order –Polyimide:510MPa, Polyethylene Terephthalate (PET):450MPa, Teflon:217MPa, Polyvinyl Chloride (PVC):110MPa.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following plastics is opaque?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyethylene Terephthalate (PET)",
            "b) Polycarbonate (PE)",
            "c) Polyphenylene Sulfide (PPS)",
            "d) Polyvinyl Chloride (PC)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transparency is related to the degree of regularity in the arrangement of molecules. This is due to the amorphous arrangement of the macromolecules. Opaque plastics have more of a semi-crystalline to crystalline arrangement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "__________ is the measure of ease with which one layer slides over another layer of plastic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flex Resistance",
            "b) Blocking",
            "c) Coefficient of friction",
            "d) Crease Resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Opaque plastics are those which block all lights and doesn’t let light to pass through it. Some plastics like Polyphenylene Sulfide are naturally opaque in nature. Other plastics can be made opaque by using additives. However, using some techniques, even opaque plastics can be made transparent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Which of the following test is used to measure tensile strength of plastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blocking",
            "b) WVTR",
            "c) Creep Test",
            "d) OTR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coefficient of friction is the measure of ease with which one layer slides over another layer of plastic. Blocking is the ability of two films to be in such a contact, so as to eliminate any air present in between the layers. Crease or flex resistance is the resistance of a plastic against crease of flexing by repeatedly folding the film forward and backward at a given rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a term used for defining optical property?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Birefringence",
            "b) Yellowness Index",
            "c) Grammage",
            "d) Refractive Index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Creep Test is used to measure tensile strength of plastics. In this the specimen is subjected to a static load. The results are noted accordingly for long term behavior of plastics. Blocking is the ability of two films to be in such a contact, so as to eliminate any air present in between the layers. WVTR and OTR are Water Vapour and Oxygen Transmission Rates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Arrange the following in correct order of WVTR.",
        "Options": [
            "a) EVOH > PET > HDPE > Al",
            "b) Al > EVOH > HDPE > PET",
            "c) PET > EVOH > HDPE > Al",
            "d) EVOH > HDPE > PET > Al"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct order of decreasing Water Vapour Transmission Rate is Ethylene Vinyl Alcohol > Polyethylene Terephthalate > High Density Polyethylene > Aluminium. Hence, amongst the given films, Aluminium is the best water vapour barrier.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "The term OTR related to packaging films stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overall Thermal Resistance",
            "b) Outer Tear Resistance",
            "c) Oxygen Transmission Rate",
            "d) Odour Transfer Rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term OTR related to packaging films stands for oxygen transmission rate. It is the rate by which oxygen permeates through a plastic film. The plastic films having a greater oxygen transmission rate are a poor barrier against gases, especially oxygen.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "The term WVTR related to packaging films stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water vapour transmission rate",
            "b) Water vapour transient rate",
            "c) Water vapour transfer rate",
            "d) Water to vapour total ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term WVTR related to packaging films stands for Water vapour transmission rate. It is the rate by which water vapour/moisture permeates through a plastic film. The plastic films having a greater water vapour transmission rate is a poor barrier against water vapour or moisture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "WVTR is expressed as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gm2/hr",
            "b) g/m224hr",
            "c) g/m2hr",
            "d) g/cm224hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: WVTR – Water vapour transmission rate is expressed as gm2/24hr. WVTR is the quantity of water vapour in gram that will permeate from one side of a film of an area 1m2 to other in 24 hours.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Arrange the following in correct order of OTR",
        "Options": [
            "a) EVOH > PET > LDPE > HDPE",
            "b) PET > EVOH > LDPE > HDPE",
            "c) LDPE > HDPE > EVOH > PET",
            "d) LDPE > HDPE > PET > EVOH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct order of decreasing Oxygen Transmission Rate is Low Density Polyethylene > High Density Polyethylene > Polyethylene Terephthalate > Ethylene Vinyl Alcohol. Hence, amongst the given films, Ethylene Vinyl Alcohol is the best oxygen barrier.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Permeability is calculated using ________ and _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) diffusion, solubility",
            "b) permeance, solubility",
            "c) diffusion, permeance",
            "d) transmittivity, solubility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Permeability is calculated using Diffusion and Solubility. Permeability is the product of diffusion and solubility. When a gas/vapour passes through the plastic film, it solubilizes first and then diffuses through the film.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "What is the unit of coefficient of Diffusion coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) m2/s",
            "b) cm2/s",
            "c) m/s",
            "d) m2s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Permeability is the multiplication of diffusion coefficient and solubility coefficient. P=D*S. P,D,S stands for Permeability coefficient, Diffusivity Coefficient and Solubility Coefficient respectively. It is because, vapour/gas solubilizes and then diffuses through the film to reach it’s other side.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "What is the unit of coefficient of Solubility coefficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) m2s",
            "b) m2/s",
            "c) m/s",
            "d) ms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unit of coefficient of Diffusion coefficient is m2/s. Diffusion coefficient is a measure of how fast a permeate moves through the plastic polymer. It depends on degree of crystallinity of polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "What is the unit of coefficient of Permeability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) s/m2",
            "b) m2/s",
            "c) m/s",
            "d) m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The unit of coefficient of Solubility coefficient is m2/s. Solubility coefficient is a measure of how much permeate solubilises through the plastic polymer. It depends on degree of interaction between polar water molecule and polymer molecular structure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Permeability can also be calculated by the formula _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P=Qk/(AtΔP)",
            "b) P=Qt/(AkΔP)",
            "c) P=Q/(AktΔP)",
            "d) P=QA/(ktΔP)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:c\nExplanation: The unit of coefficient of Permeability is m2. Permeability can be calculate by the formula- P=Qk/(AtΔP), where, P:Permeability, Q:Quantity of permeant, k:thickness,  A:area, t:time, ΔP:pressure drop across polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "The uptake of food components such as aroma and flavour by plastic films is known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scavenging",
            "b) Broiling",
            "c) Scalding",
            "d) Scaling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. There are many plastics which act as a good water vapour barrier and a poor gas barrier. It is because of different Water Vapour Transmission and Oxygen Transmission rates. For example, EVOH has low Oxygen Transmission Rate but higher Water Vapour Transmission Rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the best Oxygen barrier?",
        "Options": [
            "a) EVOH",
            "b) PS",
            "c) PE",
            "d) PP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Permeability can also be calculated by the formula- P=Qk/(AtΔP). Where, P:Permeability, Q:Quantity of permeant, k:thickness, A:area, t:time, ΔP: pressure drop across polymer. Permeability is directly proportional to Quantity of permeant and thickness and inversely proportional to area, time and pressure difference.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Permeability can be related to which law of Food Engineering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier Law",
            "b) Kohlrausch’s Law",
            "c) Fick’s Law",
            "d) Newton’s Law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The uptake of food components such as aroma and flavour by plastic films is known as Scaling. Such plastics have a greater permeability and hence are not suitable for primary packing. Such packaging materials are either used for tertiary or pellet packing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of calender?",
        "Options": [
            "a) I type",
            "b) L type",
            "c) Z type",
            "d) M type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  M type is not a type of calender. In I type of roller setup, the rollers are placed horizontally. In L type arrangement of roller setup, is I type setup mirrored vertically. In Z type arrangement of rollers, each pair of rollers is placed at right angles to the next pair in chain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "As defined by ASTM, the thickness of a plastic film (after single extrusion) should be not more than ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25mm",
            "b) 0.50mm",
            "c) 0.01cm",
            "d) 1mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: This is a false statement. Calendering and extrusion are different processes. Extrusion is a process of passing the molten plastic through a shaping device, to give it any form. Whereas, calendering is a complementary process to film and sheet extrusion, which involves the formation of continuous sheets of controlled thickness by passing plastic materials through rollers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used for conversion of extruded plastic into sheets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cast Film Extrusion",
            "b) Slit Die Extrusion",
            "c) Blown Film Extrusion",
            "d) Micro Extrusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As defined by ASTM, the thickness of a plastic film (after single extrusion) should be not more than 0.25mm. ASTM, American Society for testing materials is an international standards organisation which functions to set standards for miscellaneous materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Tubular Extrusion is also known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flat Film Extrusion",
            "b) Blown Film Extrusion",
            "c) Slit Die Extrusion",
            "d) Cast Film Extrusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Micro Extrusion is not used for conversion of extruded plastic into sheets. Micro extrusion is the process to create comparatively smaller sized objects. Whereas, Cast Film Extrusion, Slit Die Extrusion and Blown Film Extrusion are used for conversion of extruded plastic into sheets.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Compression ratios for single screw extrusion should lie between ____ and ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2:1, 3:1",
            "b) 1:2, 4:1",
            "c) 2:1, 4:1",
            "d) 1:2, 1:3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tubular Extrusion is also known as Blown Film Extrusion. Flat Film extrusion is also known as Cast Film and Slit Die Extrusion.  Like Flat Film Extrusion, Tubular extrusion is also used to convert extruded plastic into sheets. It is done by blowing air through the center of tubular die, due to which the thin tube from extruder is inflated into a thin bubble and cooled, after which it is flattened and wound up.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "The term BUR in extrusion and calendering of thermoplastics refers to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blow Up Ratio",
            "b) Bauxime Up Ratio",
            "c) Bottom Upper Ratio",
            "d) Bottom Up Ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Compression ratios for single screw extrusion should lie between 2:1 and 4:1. Compression ratio is an important parameter for any extrusion process. Compression ratio is the ratio of the volume of one flight of the screw at the in-fees end to the volume of one flight at the die end.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": " ________ is a process which combines layers of two or more plastics together at the point of extrusion.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lamination",
            "b) Plating",
            "c) Co-extrusion",
            "d) Calendering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term BUR in extrusion and calendering of thermoplastics refers to Blow Up Ratio. It is the ratio of bubble diameter to die diameter. BUR for most blown films in packaging generally lies between 2:1 and 4:1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "A single laminate layer is thicker than _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 μm",
            "b) 6 μm",
            "c) 1 μm",
            "d) 10 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:b\nExplanation: A single laminate layer is thicker than 6µm. A laminate is made up of two or more layers which can be plastic or non-plastic. But at least one layer must be a plastic. All layers to make a laminate must be thicker than 6 μm. However, there is no upper limit for this.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "In the process of surface treatment before lamination or coating, the surface energy is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant",
            "b) Decreased 10 fold",
            "c) Increased",
            "d) Decreased"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The above statement is false. Coating is the process of applying one or more layers of a fluid or melt to the surface of a material, while laminating is the bonding of two or more webs/layers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which of the following treatments increases the surface energy by using electricity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemical Treatment",
            "b) Priming",
            "c) Flame Treatment",
            "d) Corona Treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Materials other than a thermoplastic can be used in a laminate. A laminate is defined as any combination of distinctly different plastic film materials or plastic plus non plastic materials (typically paper and aluminium foil).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "For Flame Treatment prior to laminating and coating, the temperature time combination is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000-4000°C, 5s",
            "b) 1000-2800°C, 1s",
            "c) 3000-5000°C,10s",
            "d) 1000-2800°C, 15s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the process of surface treatment before lamination or coating, the surface energy is increased. This is done to improve wet-out and adhesion of coatings, inks and adhesives used. Improved wet-out maximises the contact area and attractive forces between the films.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Optimum primer weight for priming films is defined in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) mg/m2",
            "b) μg/m2",
            "c) mg/cm2",
            "d) mg/mm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Corona treatment involves the application of a high voltage (10–40 kV) low frequency (10–20 kHz) discharge across a fixed air gap between an electrode and an earthed conductive roller which carries the film. The corona treatment cleans, oxidizes and activates the surface by converting it from a nonpolar to a polar state by bombarding it with ozone, O2 and free radicals of O2. This increases the surface energy and results in the substrate surface being more compatible with a freshly oxidized thermoplastic surface, thus promoting adhesion between the two.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes is done to remove surface contaminants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Priming",
            "b) Chemical Treatment",
            "c) Corona Treatment",
            "d) Flame Treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For Flame Treatment prior to laminating and coating, the temperature time combination is 1000-2800°C, 1s. If the temperature or time increases, the film degrades and becomes weak. If the temperature or time is less than required, the film would have a lower surface energy than required.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following plastics is used in the lamination of paperboards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LDPE",
            "b) PS",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) HDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Optimum primer weight for priming films is defined in mg/m2. The quantity of primer is a critical aspect because thicker primer results in lesser cohesive forces and hence loss of adhesiveness. Thinner primer wouldn’t result in required adhesion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is used for solventless laminating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium silicate",
            "b) Polyester isocyanate",
            "c) Rubber latex",
            "d) Dextrin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemical treatment is an essential step in surface treatment to remove surface contaminants. Rest of the treatments- priming, corona treatment and flame treatment are mainly done for increasing surface energy. Chemical treatment has mainly three steps- cleaning, etching and rinsing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Which of the following lamination methods doesn’t require an adhesive for lamination?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry bonding lamination",
            "b) Solventless lamination",
            "c) Extrusion lamination",
            "d) Wet bonding lamination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LDPE is used in the lamination of paperboards. Compares to other thermoplastics, LDPE- Low Density Polyethylene offers a greater strength, seal integrity and resistance to cracking and flaking off. It also provides a greater resistance to moisture and has greater flexibility.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "ASTM stands for _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) American Society for Testing Machines",
            "b) American Society for Tempering Machines",
            "c) American Society for Testing and Measurements",
            "d) American Society for Testing Materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polyester isocyanate is used for solventless laminating. Solventless laminating is the process of bonding together two webs by curing in absence of solvents. Polyester isocyanates is used for curing the laminate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is the outermost lamination layer in tetrapacks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyester",
            "b) Polypropylene",
            "c) Polyethylene",
            "d) Polystyrene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Extrusion lamination doesn’t require an adhesive for lamination. It causes adhesion by heat and pressure during the process of extrusion. Dry and wet bonding lamination used aqueous or solvent based adhesives. Solventless lamination uses a curing agent for adhesion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Polymers used for packaging films must have a surface energy – _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-25 mNm-1",
            "b) 29-45 mNm-1",
            "c) 45-55 mNm-1",
            "d) 10-25 mNm-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ASTM stands for American Society for Testing Materials. ASTM is an international standards organisation which sets up standards for various miscellaneous materials including metals and plastics.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Smart blending works on the principle of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chaotic addition",
            "b) Chaotic advection",
            "c) Chaotic adversion",
            "d) Chaotic abstraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Smart blending works on the principle of chaotic advection. It refers to the chaotic (non-periodic) motion of a particle in a fluid that can occur even where the flow field is simple and periodic, which causes successive shear deformations and reorientations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "A __________ is a highly concentrated blend of an additive and a carrier resin.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Masterpolymer",
            "b) Mastermixture",
            "c) Masterbatch",
            "d) Masterblend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A masterbatch is a highly concentrated blend of an additive and a carrier resin. A masterbatch is a highly concentrated blend of an additive with a a carrier resin that should be compatible and miscible in the resin into which it is being blended. Film manufacturers commonly blend a masterbatch into the resin at the extruder feed hopper when making film or sheet.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Which of the following metal is not used in vacuum metallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium",
            "b) Nickel",
            "c) Chromium",
            "d) Sodium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sodium is not used in metallization. Vacuum metallization is a method in physical vapour deposition process and produces coatings by thermal evaporation of metals in a vacuum. Physical method includes vaporization of the metal, which is later deposited on the surface by condensation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a heating source in metallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Convection heating",
            "b) Resistance heating",
            "c) Induction heating",
            "d) Electron beam heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Convection heating is not a heating source in metallization. In resistance heating, aluminium wire is fed onto a block of metal that is heated by holding it in a carbon crucible or boat across which a high current is arched.  A pool of melted metal forms in the boat cavity and evaporates into a cloud above the source. In induction heating, heating is done by passing  a high current through heating coils, causing an induced magnetic field inside the coils. In electron beam heating, the source is heated by electron beam.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Energy of an electron is upto ______ in electron beam heating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15eV",
            "b) 15keV",
            "c) 30eV",
            "d) 30keV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Energy of an electron is upto 15keV in electron beam heating. Electron beam heating allows tight control of the evaporation rate and although more expensive, it is notably simpler and much more versatile as it can be used to evaporate many different materials. It must be ensured that no secondary electrons impinge on the polymeric web.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "__________ is a PVD technique in which the bulk material is released into the vacuum by bombardment from an ion source.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Splattering",
            "b) Sputtering",
            "c) Splashing",
            "d) Spreading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Metallization process has a strong and complex effect on the development of adhesive and barrier properties of metallized films. Thicker films leads to adhesion problems and even flaking, if the metallized layer becomes too thick. The thinner coatings tend to be full of pinholes and may even be transmitted lights to some degree.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "_____________ involves depositing successive layers of different substances to produce layered, crystalline films.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atomic layer chemical vapor deposition",
            "b) Combustion chemical vapor deposition",
            "c) Low pressure chemical vapor deposition",
            "d) Plasma enhanced chemical vapor deposition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sputtering is a PVD technique in which the bulk material is released into the vacuum by bombardment from an ion source. The material coalesces onto the substrate surface, thus forming a thin film.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "In Plasma Enhanced Chemical Vapor Deposition, deposition occurs at a _______ temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher",
            "b) Constant",
            "c) Increasing",
            "d) Lower"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Atomic layer chemical vapor deposition (ALCVD) involves depositing successive layers of different substances to produce layered, crystalline films. In short, ALCVD is a method in chemical vapor deposition in which deposition occurs through chemisorption of pulsed chemical reactant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which film is used for improving barrier properties of PET bottles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PVC",
            "b) PED",
            "c) DLC",
            "d) GLC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Plasma Enhanced Chemical Vapor Deposition, deposition occurs at a low temperature. The use of plasma helps to deposit thin films from a gaseous state to a solid state on the substrate; hence it enhances chemical reaction rates. The plasma is created by alternating or direct current discharge between two electrodes. The space between electrodes is filled with reacting gases which contains reactive ions and radicals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which of the following CVD technique is a flame based technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CCVD",
            "b) PECVD",
            "c) LPCVD",
            "d) ALCVD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: DLC (Diamond like Carbon) film is used for improving barrier properties of PET bottles. There is deposition of a very thin DLC film on the inner surface of PET bottle by PECVD mechanism. DLC film provides gas barrier properties, flavour barrier, UV barrier, chemical inertness, recyclability, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "The term BOPP in packaging stands for _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biaxially Oriented Polypropylene",
            "b) Biaxially Oriented Propylene Alcohol",
            "c) Biaxially Oriented polyphenol",
            "d) Biaxially Operated Packaging Printing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term BOPP in packaging stands for Biaxially Oriented Polypropylene. It is generally used for packaging labels. BOPP is produced by stretching the polypropylene film in both directions. It results in higher strength and higher resistance to stress cracking and puncture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for shrink bundle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) BOPP",
            "b) PVC",
            "c) LLDPE",
            "d) Cast PP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: LLDPE-Linear Low Density Polyethylene is used for shrink bundling. LLDPE is a copolymer made up of ethylene and another longer olefin, whereas LDPE is a homopolymer made only of ethylene monomers. LLDPE has a greater tensile strength or resistance to harsh environment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "__________ is the process which reduces the residual strain after the extrusion process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lacquering",
            "b) Canning",
            "c) Electroplating",
            "d) Annealing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above statement is false. Oriented film cannot be easily heat sealed because it shrinks and puckers at temperatures below the sealing temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "The film after annealing is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strict film",
            "b) Film set",
            "c) Heat set",
            "d) Heat film"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The given statement is true. LDPE is generally irradiated before moulding into film, because radiation cross-links the molecules and the film can be stretched without becoming fluid at the melting point of a non-irradiated film, resulting in greatly improved tensile strength and shrink tension compared to non-irradiated LDPE.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods are used for orientation of plastic films?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tenter frame and bubble frame",
            "b) Tenter frame and Double bubble",
            "c) Tenter bubble and Double bubble",
            "d) Tenter bubble and Double Frame"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Annealing is the process which reduces the residual strain after the extrusion process. Films can be annealed by the application of heat to partially relax the forces while maintaining the film in a highly stretched condition. It is then cooled to room temperature and the restraint on the film released.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "The temperature of orientation is ______ the flow temperature and _____ the glass transition temperature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) above, above",
            "b) above, below",
            "c) below, below",
            "d) below, above"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The film after annealing is called heat set. Heat set does not shrink even if heated below the annealing temperature. Heat set has more desirable properties. Annealing results in some reduction in dimension in the stretched direction or directions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not affect stretch rate in tender frame process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extent of orientation",
            "b) Divergence angle",
            "c) Feed rate",
            "d) Chain speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tenter frame and Double bubble are the two methods are used for orientation of plastic films. It generally includes heating of the film and stretching it in uniaxial or biaxial direction on a tenter or double frame. The orientation decides the use of the film.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Draw ratios in tender frame process ranges from ______ to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4:1, 10:1",
            "b) 2:1, 10:1",
            "c) 3:1, 10:1",
            "d) 5:1, 10:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperature of orientation is below the flow temperature and above the glass transition temperature. When the temperature of the film is above glass transition temperature and below flow temperature, the molecules readily glide past one another when the material is stressed. This is the optimal temperature for stretching the thermoplastic film. As a result of this stretching, the direction of the molecules changes toward that in which the material is stressed, and the molecules are extended like springs. The lower temperature enables the setting the configuration of molecules in the strained position.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "The orientation % in BOPP by the double bubble process lies between _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200-1000",
            "b) 200-800",
            "c) 700-800",
            "d) 700-1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Orientation decreases permeability. It is because orientation decreases both, the diffusion and solubility coefficient of the plastic film.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "The property of a thermoplastic film to return to its original size is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elasticity",
            "b) Shrinkiness",
            "c) Elastic memory",
            "d) Shrinkability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Feed rate does not affect stretch rate in tender frame process. Stretch rate is determined by the chain speed, divergence angle and extent of orientation. The thermoplastic film is stretched in the machine direction (MD) and the extent of orientation is determined by the ratio of the width of the film entering to the width of the film leaving the system. The film is then fed to a tender frame where a series of clips (mounted side by side on endless chains that diverge at constant angle) grasp both edges of the film and draw it in the transverse direction (TD) as it travels forward at an increasing speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not used as a stretch film?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyolefins",
            "b) PVC",
            "c) PVdC",
            "d) PET"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PET is not used as a stretch film. PET has its greatest use in bottles for juices and soft drink due to its barrier and mechanical properties. Shrink films are composed of three basic categories: polyolefins, PVC and PVdC copolymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "LLDPE is produced by copolymerisation of ethylene with ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Di-olefins",
            "b) Gamma olefins",
            "c) Beta olefins",
            "d) Alpha olefins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LLDPE is produced by copolymerisation of ethylene with alpha olefins. LLDPE- Linear Low Density Polyethylene has better stretch properties when compared to LDPE- Low Density Polyethylene.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "PVDC stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyvinylidene Chloride",
            "b) Polyvinyl Dichloride",
            "c) Polyvinyldeca Chloride",
            "d) Polyvinyldiene Chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PVDC stands for Polyvinylidene Chloride. PVdC is a polymer of Vinylidene chloride. PVDC is also known as coated PVC. PVDC has lower OTR and WVTR when compared to PVC, by a factor of 5-10.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "BOPP stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biaxially operated polypropylene",
            "b) Biaxiallyoriented propylene",
            "c) Biaxiallyoriented packaged propylene",
            "d) Biaxially oriented polypropylene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above statement is false. A plastic wrap is same as shrink wrap. It is the shrink wrap used in foods. It is used to wrap food items, so as to preserve them for a longer period of time. The most commonly used plastic wrap is PVC.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Find the odd one.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cling film",
            "b) Plastic wrap",
            "c) Saran wrap",
            "d) Stretch film"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: BOPP stands for biaxially oriented polypropylene. BOPP is mostly used in packaging labels. It is a product of heat-setting, the process in which a film is reheated in a constrained strain. It is produced by the tenderframe technology for orientation of plastic films.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "In __________ no sealing is required.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plating",
            "b) Laminating",
            "c) Stretch wrapping",
            "d) Shrink wrapping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stretch film is the odd one. Cling film, plastic wrap and saran wrap are the terms which denote a thin plastic film used for packaging of food. It is also known as shrink wrap and food wrap. Stretch film is used for wrapping secondary or higher forms of packaging. It can never be used as a primary packaging material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Which of the following polymer is used as a shrink film for foods and snacks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PE",
            "b) PP",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) Polyolefin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In stretch wrapping, no sealing is required. Its main function is pallet unitizing. During stretch wrapping, the material is covered in such a way that the film’s elasticity holds the load tightly together and hence, no sealing is required.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following polymer is used as a shrink film for CDs and DVDs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PE",
            "b) PP",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) Polyolefin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polyolefin films are used for shrink wrapping of foods, snacks and retail items. It is a clear film that shrinks evenly in all directions. This film allows scents to permeate it. Since it requires high temperatures to shrink the film, it’s often applied with a shrink wrap machine which increases productivity and allows items to be bundled together.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "Which of the following polymer is used for wrapping large and bulky items?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PE",
            "b) PP",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) Polyolefin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PVC- Polyvinyl Chloride is used as a shrink film for CDs and DVDs (and also Blu-ray discs). PVC shrink films have high strength with good clarity and gloss. Its major use is in shrink wrapping CDs, DVDs and discs, but is also used for shrink wrapping of books, toys and food items.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which of the following polymer is also called general purpose shrink film?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PE",
            "b) PP",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) Polyolefin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above statement is false. Thermosetting plastics cannot be used as shrink or stretch films. There are only four types of thermoplastics used for shrink wrapping currently, which include – Polyethylene, Polypropylene, Polyolefin and Polyvinyl Chloride.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of overwrap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decorative wrap",
            "b) Paper wrap",
            "c) Stretch wrap",
            "d) Shrink wrap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PE- Polyethylene is used for wrapping large and bulky items. PE shrink films are thicker, stronger and more durable than other shrink films. PE shrink films are often used to wrap bottled water, canned goods and other heavy objects. It is deal for wrapping large and bulky items during transit. These films are so strong that they can replace corrugated boxes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "In thermoforming, plastic sheets are heated to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boiling point",
            "b) Tg point",
            "c) Sag point",
            "d) Melting point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In thermoforming, plastic sheets are heated to Sag point. It is the temperature at which the plastic softens and extends under its own weight, i.e., when the plastic begins to sag.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "From which of the following processes, canopies for racing vehicles are made?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drape forming",
            "b) Mechanical forming",
            "c) Pressure forming",
            "d) Free blowing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Canopies for racing vehicles are made from drape forming. Drape forming is the process by which the plastic sheet is heated, such that it can be bent and shaped into any form without using a vacuum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "SPPF in thermoforming stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soluble peer pressure forming",
            "b) Soluble phase pressure forming",
            "c) Solid peer pressure forming",
            "d) Solid phase pressure forming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SPPF in thermoforming stands for solid phase pressure forming. The SPPF process is primarily used to thermoform PP, a crystalline polymer that is difficult to thermoform uniformly in melt phase machines due to the sharp decrease in melt strength (viscosity) at its melting point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "In drape forming technique _______ is used for forming.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vacuum",
            "b) High pressure",
            "c) High Temperature",
            "d) Low pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. CPET (Crystalline PET) is stable till 230°C. Whereas, APET (Amorphous PET) softens over 63°C. The CPET process is based on conventional reheat thermoforming where an extruded PET sheet containing nucleating agents to speed up and maximize crystallization is reheated to around 170°C where it softens. After this, it is transferred in a hot mold and held so the crystallinity develops. Then it is transferred to a second mould for cooling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is not thermoformed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HIPS & ABS",
            "b) POM & Nylon",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) PMMA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In drape forming technique vacuum is used for forming. In vacuum forming, vacuum is heated below the preheated plastic sheet to draw sheet into cold mold cavity. The steps include heating the plastic sheet, placing the softened sheet is placed over a concave activity. Vacuum draws the sheet into cold cavity. The final product is then cooled.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Bath tubs are made by __________ technique.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Free forming",
            "b) Pressure thermoforming",
            "c) Match die thermoforming",
            "d) Drape forming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Among the given options, POM & Nylon is not thermoformed. Whereas, HIPS- High Impact Polystyrene,  ABS- Acrylonitrile Butadiene Styrene, PVC- Polyvinyl Chloride and PMMA- Poly(methyl methacrylate) are thermoformed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Thermoforming can be generally classified as ________ and _______ thermoforming.",
        "Options": [
            "a) pressure, temperature",
            "b) vacuum, pressure",
            "c) Thick gauge, thin gauge",
            "d) Temperature, vacuum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bath tubs are made by drape forming technique. Drape forming is the process by which the plastic sheet is heated, such that it can be bent and shaped into any form without using a vacuum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a mold used in thermoforming?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium mold",
            "b) Steel mold",
            "c) Wooden mold",
            "d) Plastic mold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thermoforming can be generally classified as Thick gauge and thin gauge thermoforming. Thick gauge thermoforming is a term used for making heavy duty parts, such as- plastic pallets, refrigerator liners, etc. Whereas, thin-gauge thermoforming is the term used to describe the manufacturing of lighter and smaller things, such as disposable cups, containers, trays, lids, and other products for the food, medical, and general retail industries.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "The CPET containers, made by thermoforming are stable upto what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 230°C",
            "b) 150°C",
            "c) 300°C",
            "d) 500°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Steel mold is not used in thermoforming. The mould used in thermoforming should be such that the plastic polymer to be thermoformed isn’t affected by it. The mold used in thermoforming are- aluminium mold, plaster of paris mold, plastic mold and wooden mold.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The two dominant means of thermoforming sheet for food packaging containers are _____ & _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid phase pressure forming, liquid phase pressure forming",
            "b) Liquid phase process, vapour phase pressure forming",
            "c) Melt phase process, liquid phase pressure forming",
            "d) Melt phase process , solid phase pressure forming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statemet is false. Thermoforming and blow moulding are totally different processes. Thermoforming is the process in which an article is heated stretched and cooled to give it a desirable shape. Whereas, in blow moulding, the thermoplastic is heated and put into the desired container and then shaped by blowing air through it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "_______ are defined as plastics whose apparent density is decreased.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellular plastics",
            "b) Polyplastics",
            "c) Thermoplastics",
            "d) Artificial plastics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: CPET (Crystallized Polyethylene terephthalate)containers, made by thermoforming are stable upto 230°C. The optimum amount of crystallinity is 28%–32%. CPET containers must be crystalline enough to be heat resistant but not so crystalline as to be too brittle for the application, for example, impact resistance at freezer temperatures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Molten tube of thermoplastic is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parison",
            "b) Thermotube",
            "c) Parrison",
            "d) Tubling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Molten tube of thermoplastic is called parison. It is a long plastic tube, with a hole, to let compressed air pass through it. Making parison is the first step of blow moulding.  Parison is also known as Preform.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Small pharmaceutical bottles with accurate neck finish is formed by _______ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calendering",
            "b) Injection Blow Moulding",
            "c) Extrusion Blow Moulding",
            "d) Rotational Moulding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Small pharmaceutical bottles with accurate neck finish are formed by Injection blow moulding process. In injection moulding process, the parison is formed in one mold and then, while still molten, is transferred to a second mold where blowing with compressed air forms the final shape. After cooling, the mold is opened and the bottle is ejected.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of Blow moulding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Injection stretch blow molding",
            "b) Injection blow molding",
            "c) Thermoforming",
            "d) Extrusion blow molding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thermoforming is not a type of Blow moulding. There are three main types of blow molding- extrusion blow molding, injection blow molding, and injection stretch blow molding. Thermoforming is a different process in which thermoplastics are converted into desirable shape by heating and stretching.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Which of the plastics cannot be extrusion blown?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDPE",
            "b) PP",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) PET"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The common grades of PET(Polyethylene Terephthalate) cannot be extrusion blown. Extrusion blow moulding is widely used with the following resins: HDPE- High Density Polyethylene, PP- Polypropylene, PVC- Polyvinyl Chloride. The most common blow molding resin is HDPE used to produce containers ranging in size from 30 mL to 200L.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Two stage stretch blow moulding is also known as _________ method.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extrusion",
            "b) Reheat and blow method",
            "c) Thermoforming",
            "d) Injection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Two stage stretch blow moulding is also known as reheat and blow method method. In this, the parisons are first injection molded in a completely separate stage and stored at ambient temperature until required. Then, they are are then reheated to between 90°C and 110°C and blown to their final shape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "The most widely used polymer in Stretch Blow Moulding is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) PE",
            "b) PVC",
            "c) PP",
            "d) PET"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most widely used polymer in Stretch Blow Moulding is PET- Polyethylene Terephthalate. PET is used in the manufacture of carbonated beverages packing bottles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "_________ improves strength and barrier properties of plastic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stretching",
            "b) Blowing",
            "c) Heating",
            "d) Cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above statement is false. The IBM produces smoother finished parts which are scrap free, when compared to EBM. In addition to that, the dimensions of the bottle (including the neck finish) show very little variation from bottle to bottle, and with some materials, improved strength and clarity are obtained due to the effect of a limited degree of biaxial orientation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Pressure used in IBM ranges from _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2,000 – 3,000 psi",
            "b) 100 – 500 psi",
            "c) 500 – 800 psi",
            "d) 25 – 150 psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stretching improves strength and barrier properties of plastic. It happens because the orientation and arrangement of monomers changes, hence changing the strength and barrier properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Pressure used in Blow moulding in general ranges from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 – 2000 psi",
            "b) 200 – 500 psi",
            "c) 500 – 800 psi",
            "d) 25 – 150 psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pressure used in IBM ranges from 2,000 – 3,000 psi. Because of this, there is a development of high internal stresses in this process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "________ is used to obtain bioriented products.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extrusion blow molding",
            "b) Stretch blow moulding",
            "c) Injection blow molding",
            "d) Thermoforming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pressure used in Blow moulding in general ranges from 25-150 psi. Blow moulding, in general is a low pressure process, to make hollow and seemless parts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "The reheating temperature in reheat and blow method ranges from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 180° – 250°C",
            "b) 90° – 110°C",
            "c) 150° – 200°C",
            "d) 200° – 250°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stretch blow moulding is used to obtain bioriented products. In injection stretch blow moulding, the process begins with an injection moulded parison. The parison is pre-heated, stretched in the axial direction and blown into its final shape by a stretch blow moulding machine, which results in changing its orientation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Cull is associated with _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotational moulding",
            "b) Injection moulding",
            "c) Auxiliary ram type transfer moulding",
            "d) Pot type transfer moulding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. PTFE-Polytetrafluoroethylene can only be processed through compression moulding. In this process, the plastic is heated and simply moulded, where the plastic takes the shape of the mould.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "PS foams are produced by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) injection moulding and extrusion moulding",
            "b) extrusion moulding only",
            "c) injection moulding only",
            "d) stretch blow moulding only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reheating temperature in reheat and blow method ranges from 90° – 110°C. After reheating the plastics, they are blown into their final shape.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "The fibrous raw material for production of paper is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulp",
            "b) Hemicellulose",
            "c) Cellulose",
            "d) Lignin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pulp is the fibrous raw material for the production of paper, paperboard, corrugated board and similar manufactured products. It is obtained from plant fiber and is therefore a renewable resource.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Paper derives its name from _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Papyres",
            "b) Pyrus",
            "c) Palpable",
            "d) Papyrus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Paper derives its name from the reedy plant papyrus, which the ancient Egyptians used to produce the world’s first writing material by beating and pressing together thin layers of the plant stem.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a constituent of the wood cell wall?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose",
            "b) Pectin",
            "c) Hemicellulose",
            "d) Lignin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pectin is not a constituent of the wood cell wall. It is a heteropolysaccharide present in primary cell walls of plants. It is responsible for the structural integrity of the cell. There are three main constituents of the wood cell wall – Cellulose, Hemicellulose and Lignin.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Paper greater than _______ g/m2 is called paperboard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200g/m2",
            "b) 100g/m2",
            "c) 500g/m2",
            "d) 300g/m2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Paper greater than 200g/m2 (GSM) is called paperboard, as defined by ISO. GSM- Gram per square meter is used to express the amount of fiber. Paperboard is thicker than paper and has a higher weight per unit area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "_______ refers to the process wherein wood or other fibrous raw materials are reduced to a fibrous mass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pulping",
            "b) Forming",
            "c) Sheeting",
            "d) Draping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pulping refers to the process wherein wood or other fibrous raw materials are reduced to a fibrous mass. Pulping is done to separate the fibers without damaging them so that they can then be reformed into a paper sheet in the papermaking process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "________ expresses the lignin content of pulp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beta number",
            "b) Gamma number",
            "c) Kappa number",
            "d) Alpha number"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Softwood Hardwood fibers are longer than that of hardwood fibers. Compared to hardwoods, softwoods have fibers that are generally up to 2.5 times longer. As a result, hardwoods produce a finer, smoother but less strong sheet.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "When was the first authentic paper made?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 AD",
            "b) 100 AD",
            "c) 105 AD",
            "d) 500 AD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Hardwood has more amount of cellulose and hemicellulose present in it. Hardwood has about 45% cellulose and 30% hemicellulose, whereas, softwood has about 42% cellulose and 27% hemicellulose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "________ has no fiber forming properties.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lignin",
            "b) Cellulose",
            "c) Hemicellulose",
            "d) Glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Kappa number expresses the lignin content of pulp. A high kappa number indicates a high lignin content. The kappa number of bleachable softwood and hardwood pulps is 30–40 and 18–20 respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "______ is lower MW mixed-sugar polysaccharides.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lignin",
            "b) Cellulose",
            "c) Hemicellulose",
            "d) Glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first authentic papermaking, which is the formation of a cohesive sheet from the rebonding of separated fibers, has been attributed to Ts’ai-Lun of China in 105 AD, who used bamboo, mulberry bark and rags.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "________ mainly determines the paper properties.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lignin",
            "b) Cellulose",
            "c) Hemicellulose",
            "d) Glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. The principal hemicelluloses are xylan in hardwoods and glucomannon in softwoods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "______ is the natural binding constituent of the cells of wood and plant stalks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lignin",
            "b) Cellulose",
            "c) Hemicellulose",
            "d) Glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lignin has no fiber-forming properties. This is the natural binding constituent of the cells of wood and plant stalks. It is a highly branched, three-dimensional (3D), alkylaromatic, thermoplastic polymer of uncertain size, built up largely from substituted phenylpropane or propylbenzene units.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "_______ softens at 160°C.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pectin",
            "b) Hemicellulose",
            "c) Cellulose",
            "d) Lignin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hemicellulose is lower MW mixed-sugar polysaccharides, consisting of one or more of the following molecules: xylose, mannose, arabinose, galactose and uronic acids, with the composition differing from species to species.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "______ is the intercellular substance remaining in fiber pulp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose",
            "b) Pectin",
            "c) Glucose",
            "d) Lignin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The purpose of pulping is to separate the fibers without damaging them so that they can then be reformed into a paper sheet in the papermaking process. Pulping refers to the process wherein wood or other fibrous raw materials are reduced to a fibrous mass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "If ________ is present in paper, it deteriorates in color and strength quite rapidly.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose",
            "b) Lignin",
            "c) Hemicellulose",
            "d) Pectin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lignin is the intercellular substance remaining in fiber pulp. Lignin must be softened or dissolved to free individual fibers. Commercial pulping methods take advantage of the differences between the properties of cellulose and lignin in order to separate fibers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "________ pulp is produced by forcing wood against a rapidly revolving grindstone.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grindwood",
            "b) Groundwood",
            "c) Pinewood",
            "d) Smashwood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If lignin is present in paper, it deteriorates in color and strength quite rapidly. Pulps that retain most of the wood lignin consist of stiff fibers that do not produce strong papers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of the following pulping processes was developed in 1950s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulphite process",
            "b) Kraft process",
            "c) Refiner mechanical pulping process",
            "d) Screw pulping process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Groundwood pulp is produced by forcing wood against a rapidly revolving grindstone. The heat generated by friction softens the lignin so that the fibers separate with very little damage. In this, practically all the wood fiber (both cellulose and lignin) is utilized.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The presteaming temperature for thermochemical pulping is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 110°C – 150°C",
            "b) 150°C – 200°C",
            "c) 200°C – 250°C",
            "d) 250°C – 300°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. The yield of chemical pulp is less than that of mechanical pulp. It is about one-half that of the mechanical process. It is because all the wood fiber (both cellulose and lignin) is utilized. This contrasts with several chemical processes where the lignin is dissolved to varying degrees.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Paper from which pulp is mostly used for newspaper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Groundwood pulp",
            "b) Thermochemical pulp",
            "c) Chemithermomechanical pulp",
            "d) Kraft process pulp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the 1950s, the refiner mechanical pulping (RMP) process was developed, which produced a stronger pulp and utilized various supplies of wood chips, sawmill residues and sawdust. RMP results in more long fibers than stone groundwood and subsequently stronger paper. However, the energy requirements of RMP are higher and the pulp does not have the opacity of groundwood fibers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Which pulping process is suitable for manufacturing of the middle layer of multi-ply boards?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical pupling",
            "b) Kraft pulping",
            "c) Thermomechanical pulping",
            "d) Chemithermomechanical pulping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thermomechanical pulping (TMP) presteams chips between 110°C and 150°C so that they become malleable and do not fracture readily under the impact of the refiner bars. This material is highly flexible and gives good bonding and surface smoothing to the paper.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "What is used for pretreatment in Chemithermomechanical pulping?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium propionate",
            "b) Calcium carbonate",
            "c) Sodium nitrate",
            "d) Sodium sulfite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Groundwood pulp contains a considerable proportion (70%–80%) of fiber bundles, broken fibers and fines in addition to the individual fibers. The fibers are essentially wood with the original cell wall lignin intact. Therefore, they are very stiff and bulky, and does not collapse like the chemical pulp fibers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Chemical pulping mostly uses which of the following chemical?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium Nitrate",
            "b) Potassium Hydroxide",
            "c) Calcium Carbonate",
            "d) Sodium Hydroxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All chemical pulping methods are based, either directly or indirectly, on the use of sodium hydroxide.  The chemical is selectively chosen, because, the nature of the pulping chemicals influences the properties of the residual lignin and the residual carbohydrates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "The kappa number of bleachable softwood pulps is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-20",
            "b) 20-30",
            "c) 30-40",
            "d) 40-50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The primary goal of chemical pulping is to selectively remove as much lignin as possible, especially from the middle lamella, without degrading the carbohydrate components and negatively effecting pulp properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "The kappa number of bleachable hardwood pulps is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20–30",
            "b) 30–40",
            "c) 10–20",
            "d) 18–20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The kappa number of bleachable softwood pulps is 30–40. The pulp and paper industry uses the “kappa number” to express the lignin content of a pulp, a high kappa number indicating high lignin content.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Kraft process is also known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soda process",
            "b) Sulphate process",
            "c) Sulphite process",
            "d) Semichemical process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The kappa number of bleachable hardwood pulps is 18–20. This indicates that hardwood pulp has lower lignin content than softwood pulp. Lignin does not have fiber forming properties, hence, hardwood pulp does not make as strong paper as softwood pulp.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as the white liquor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium hydroxide and Sodium hydride",
            "b) Sodium sulphite and Sodium sulphate",
            "c) Sodium sulphate and Sodium hydroxide",
            "d) Sodium hydride only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Chemical pulping method uses alkali for the process. It includes- soda process, kraft process and sulfite process, all of which used sodium hydroxide (alkali) either directly or indirectly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first alkaline process to be developed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soda process",
            "b) Sulphate process",
            "c) Sulphite process",
            "d) Kraft process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Kraft process is also known as sulphate process. It is commonly called kraft, because it is the German and Swedish word for strength. The new sulfate process produced a much stronger pulp than that from the soda process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "The soda process consisted of boiling wood _____ in sodium hydroxide liquor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%–2%",
            "b) 3%–5%",
            "c) 2%–3%",
            "d) 4%–6%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A solution of sodium hydroxide and sodium hydride is also known as the white liquor. It is widely used in the chemical pulping industry for cooking the wood chips, hence, also called cooking liquor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Kraft Process was developed in the year _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1750",
            "b) 1850",
            "c) 1879",
            "d) 1995"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Soda process was the first alkaline process to be developed. It was invented by Englishmen Hugh Burgess and Charles Watt in 1851 and was patented in 1854. The first successful soda mill commenced operation in 1866.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "‘Dissolving pulp” is obtained by which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Semichemical process",
            "b) Sulphite process",
            "c) Kraft process",
            "d) Soda process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The soda process consisted of boiling wood in 4%–6% sodium hydroxide liquor at a high temperature (170°C). This process is now obsolete. Less than 2% of the pulp produced today uses this process which is very similar to the sulfate process, except that only sodium hydroxide is used. Essentially all former soda mills have converted to the sulfate process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods is mostly used for making glassine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soda process",
            "b) Kraft process",
            "c) Semichemical process",
            "d) Sulphite process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1879, German chemist Carl F. Dahl developed the Kraft (sulfate) method of pulping wood. The process was essentially a modification of the soda process, but instead of sodium hydroxide, sodium sulfate was the major chemical used as the cooking liquor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "The _______ uses sodium sulfite and a small amount of sodium hydroxide or sodium carbonate to give slightly alkaline liquor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basic-sulfite semichemical (NSSC) process",
            "b) Acidic-sulfite semichemical (NSSC) process",
            "c) Neutral-sulfite semichemical (NSSC) process",
            "d) Alkaline-sulfite semichemical (NSSC) process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ‘Dissolving pulp” is obtained by sulphite process. It is a special grade of bleached sulfite pulp and is used for a variety of cellulose derivatives including RCF and cellulose acetate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "______ is the process after pulping.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rolling",
            "b) Bleaching",
            "c) Digestion",
            "d) Sheeting"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Digestion is the process after pulping. The digestion process essentially consists of treating wood in chip form in a pressurized vessel under controlled conditions of time, liquor concentration and pressure/temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the primary function of digestion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To separate the fibers",
            "b) To produce a well cooked pulp",
            "c) To bleach the pulp",
            "d) To increase the strength of the pulp"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The primary function of digestion is to produce a well cooked pulp, free from the non-cellulosic portions of the wood (i.e., lignin and to a certain extent hemicelluloses). It’s other functions are- to achieve a maximum yield of raw material (i.e., pulp from wood) commensurate with pulp quality and to ensure a constant supply of pulp of the correct quality.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "After steaming at ______ pressure, the chips are brought to the digester pressure of ______ kPa.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low, 500",
            "b) High, 500",
            "c) High, 1000",
            "d) Low, 1000"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: After steaming at low pressure, the chips are brought to the digester pressure of 1000 kPa. At LP, turpentine and gases are vented to the condenser. Then they are picked up in a stream of pulping solution and their temperature is raised to 170°C over 1.5 h. After holding at this temperature for a further 1.5 h, the digestion process is essentially complete.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the primary objective of bleaching?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase strength",
            "b) To maximize yield",
            "c) To increase brightness",
            "d) To remove lignin"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The first step if pulping- mechanical, chemical or semichemical, which is followed by digestion. After digestion, the liquor containing the soluble residue from the cook is washed out of the pulp, which is then screened to remove knots and fiber bundles that have not fully disintegrated. The pulp is then sent to the bleach plant or paper mill.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following component is majorly responsible for color of the pulp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose",
            "b) Lignin",
            "c) Hemicellulose",
            "d) Pectin"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Bleaching is a chemical process applied to chemical and mechanical pulps, primarily to increase their brightness but it also improves the cleanliness of pulp through removing extractives and other contaminants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "_________ present in lignin is responsible for its color.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromophores",
            "b) Corona",
            "c) Chomosomes",
            "d) Tonoplast"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: Lignin is majorly responsible for color of the pulp. It is the chromophoric groups on the lignin that are largely responsible for the color of the pulp. Cellulose and hemicelluloses are inherently white and do not contribute to color.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "________ is the term used for bleaching of mechanical pulp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Whitening",
            "b) Lightening",
            "c) Chroming",
            "d) Brightening"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Bleaching reduces the strength of the pulp. Bleaching involves both the oxidation of colored bodies and the removal of residual encrusting materials (the principal one being lignin) remaining from the digestion and washing stages. This also results in loss of strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Bleaching by hydrogen peroxide occurs at ____ °C for _____h.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40°C, 2 h",
            "b) 60°C, 2.5 h",
            "c) 40°C, 3 h",
            "d) 10°C, 4 h"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Chromophores present in lignin is responsible for its color.The density of Chromophores present in a compound determines its color.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "The residual lignin content in chemical pulp accounts for_______ of the mass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8%–9%",
            "b) 5%–8%",
            "c) 2%–5%",
            "d) 1%–2%"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: Brightening is the term used for bleaching of mechanical pulp. It is done to distinguish it from lignin-removing bleaching methods for chemical pulps. An increase in the brightness of mechanical pulps is achieved by modifying the lignin structures (chromophores) in the pulp furnish.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "The term TCF in chlorine bleaching stands for_________bleaching.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total chlorine free",
            "b) Total cadmium free",
            "c) Total chromium free",
            "d) Total calcium free"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Bleaching by hydrogen peroxide occurs at 40°C for 3 h. It is followed by neutralization and destruction of excess peroxide with SO2. These pulps may be improved in color to only a limited extent since they contain virtually all the lignin from the original wood. Peroxide bleaching allows brightness to be increased by nearly 20%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "The term ECF in chlorine bleaching stands for _________ bleaching.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elemental chromium free",
            "b) Estimated chlorine free",
            "c) Essential chlorine free",
            "d) Elemental chlorine free"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The residual lignin content in chemical pulp accounts for 2%–5% of the mass. It is responsible for the dark color of the unbleached pulp. The reagents for full bleaching of chemical pulp are mostly oxidative and since the carbohydrates are also susceptible to oxidation, bleaching must be accomplished under the mildest conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "________ is the mostly used chemical for bleaching of chemical pulp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium Hydroxide",
            "b) Potassium Iodide",
            "c) Hydrogen Peroxide",
            "d) Sodium Disulphite"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The term TCF in chlorine bleaching stands for total chlorine free bleaching. This  has been introduced to enable pulp and paper mills to meet tough new antipollution laws and regulations, and to conserve wood, chemicals and energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "__________ is the interface between the pulp mill and the papermaking process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stew preparation",
            "b) Stock preparation",
            "c) Dew preparation",
            "d) Stall preparation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stock preparation is the interface between the pulp mill and the papermaking process in which pulp is treated mechanically and, in some instances, chemically by the use of additives and is thus made ready for forming into a sheet or board on the paper machine. During the stock preparation steps, the pulps are most conveniently handled as aqueous slurries.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The separation of all the fibers from one another and their dispersion in water is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slushing",
            "b) Sheeting",
            "c) Wetting",
            "d) Mashing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The separation of all the fibers from one another and their dispersion in water is called slushing or repulping. In the papermaking process utilizing purchased pulps and waste paper which are received as dry sheets, the first step is the separation of all the fibers from one another, and their dispersion in water with a minimum of mechanical work to avoid altering the fiber properties. This process is known as slushing or repulping and is carried out in a machine such as the hydrapulper, so called because of the hydraulic forces that are developed. When the pulping and papermaking operations are adjacent to one another, pulps are usually delivered to the paper mill in slush form directly from the pulping operation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Stock (fibrous material) is prepared by which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extraction and expelling",
            "b) Beating and extraction",
            "c) Extraction and refining",
            "d) Beating and refining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stock—as fibrous material is commonly called—is prepared by two chief processes commonly referred to as beating and refining. Both operations are fundamentally the same; in many situations, the two terms are used synonymously. Beating and refining are used to improve the strength and other physical properties of the finished sheet, and to influence the behavior of the system during the sheet-forming and drying steps.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The object of beating is _________ of the fibers by assisting them to imbibe water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase the surface area",
            "b) To decrease the surface area",
            "c) To increase the volume",
            "d) To decrease the volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The object of beating is to increase the surface area of the fibers by assisting them to imbibe water. As a result, additional bonding opportunities are provided for between cellulose molecules of neighboring fibers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "After beating, the mixture of pulp is brought to a consistency of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3%–5%.",
            "b) 1%–7%.",
            "c) 5%–7%.",
            "d) 6%–9%."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mixture of pulp (known as the furnish) is passed into the beater and brought to a consistency of 5%–7%. The beating makes the fibers more flexible, causing them to become relatively mobile and to deform plastically on the paper machine.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "In many paper mills, beaters have been replaced by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous refiners",
            "b) Continuous disks",
            "c) Continuous sheets",
            "d) Continuous templates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Because papermaking fibers are stiff and springy, the resulting paper would be flabby and weak if made into a sheet of paper without beating. There would be little adhesion between the fibers and they could not be consolidated under the presses of the paper machine. A sheet formed from an unbeaten pulp has a low density, and is rather soft and weak.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a filler used in paper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Titanium dioxide",
            "b) Sodium hydroxide",
            "c) Kaolin clay",
            "d) Calcium carbonate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. If the same unbeaten pulp is beaten, then the resultant paper is much more dense, hard and strong. If taken to the extreme, beating produces very dense, translucent, glassine-type sheets. Thus, beating can be controlled to produce paper types as widely different as blotting and greaseproof paper.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to increase water resistance of paper?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Filling",
            "b) Sizing",
            "c) Stretching",
            "d) Sheeting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In many paper mills, beaters have been replaced by continuous refiners, such as disk refiners (where rotary disks rotate against a working surface) and conical refiners. However, the batch beater is a convenient vessel for adding chemicals and mixing them intimately with the pulp in order to give special properties to the final paper.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which of the following was the first paper making machine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourinder machine",
            "b) Cylinder machine",
            "c) Twin-Wire Formers",
            "d) Roller Presses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The first paper making machine was Fourdrinier machine of 1804, named after its financiers Henry and Sealy Fourdrinier, two prosperous London stationers who purchased the patent interests of the Frenchman Didot Frères. In this, paper is made by depositing a very dilute suspension of fibers from a very low consistency aqueous suspension (greater than 99% water) on to a relatively fine woven screen, over 95% of the water being removed by drainage through the wire. The fibers interlace in a generally random manner as they are deposited on the wire and become part of the filter medium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Paper greater than ________ is considered paperboard.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 μm",
            "b) 200 μm",
            "c) 500 μm",
            "d) 400 μm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Paper greater than <300 μm thick is considered paperboard, regardless of the grammage or weight per unit area. Paper is generally termed paperboard when its basis weight (grammage) exceeds 250 gm-2 (i.e., grams per square meter or GSM).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "_________ are used to produce heavy multi-ply boards.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourinder machine",
            "b) Cylinder machine",
            "c) Twin-Wire Formers",
            "d) Roller Presses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cylinder machines are used to produce heavy multi-ply boards. They produce a sheet that is much stronger in the direction of flow than that produced on Fourdrinier machines. A cylinder covered with a wire cloth is rotated partially submerged in a stock suspension. Because of a vacuum applied inside the cylinder, water drains inward through the wire cloth, and the paper web is formed on the outside. The web is picked up by a felt, which is pressed onto the top of the cylinder by a rubber roll. A series of vats provide individual plies of fiber which are subsequently matted together.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "___________ are particularly used for lightweight sheets, corrugated media and linerboard grades.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourinder machine",
            "b) Roller Presses",
            "c) Twin-wire formers",
            "d) Cylinder machine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Twin-wire formers are particularly used for lightweight sheets, corrugated media and linerboard grades. In this, the paper web is formed between two converging forming screens by means of a flow box and the water is drained from the slurry by pressure and later by vacuum. A typical twin-wire forming unit is the inverform, which was designed to provide a new method for the manufacture of single and multi-ply sheets at high speeds. Successive layers of fiber are laid down sequentially on the felt, with water being removed upwardly, overcoming the difficulty experienced in the conventional downward removal of water through several layers of board at high speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The moisture content of the paper sheet before entering the dryer is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35%–40%",
            "b) 35%–50%",
            "c) 45%–60%",
            "d) 75%–90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After leaving the forming fabric of the papermaking machine, the sheet (which has a moisture content of 75%–90% depending on type) passes to the press and dryer sections for further water removal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "The moisture content of the paper sheet after passing through the rotary presses is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80%–90%",
            "b) 60%–70%",
            "c) 40%–50%",
            "d) 10%–20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rotary presses (which may have solid or perforated rollers, often with internal suction) receive the sheets on continuous felts, which act as conveyers and porous receptors of water. On leaving the press, the moisture content is typically 60%–70%, again depending on type.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "The final moisture content of paper after pressing and drying is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4%–10%",
            "b) 10%–20%",
            "c) 1%–5%",
            "d) 40%–50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The paper is after passing through a series of steam-heated rollers is dried to a final moisture content between 4% and 10%. Other types of dryers are used for special products or situations. For example, the Yankee dryer is a large, steam-heated cylinder, which dries the sheet from one side only, and is used extensively for tissues and to produce machine glazed (MG) papers, the latter having a glazed or shiny surface from intimate contact with the polished dryer surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "The application of chemicals to the surface of a paper web is done with _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stew press",
            "b) Scaling press",
            "c) Screw press",
            "d) Size press"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The application of chemicals to the surface of a paper web is done with a size press. In a size press, the dry paper is passed through a flooded nib, where a dispersion of functional chemical contacts both sides of the paper. Excess liquid is then squeezed out in the press and the paper is re-dried.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "An optimum concentration of coating solution for improving water resistance of paperboard is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 w/v%",
            "b) 2.5 w/v%",
            "c) 3 w/v%",
            "d) 1 w/v%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An optimum concentration of coating solution for improving water resistance of paperboard was 3 w/v %. It gives a coating thickness of 28 μm equivalent to 49.5 GSM. There is an increase in the water resistance of paperboard when it is coated with PLA. A coating thickness between 4.7 to 42.7 μm decreases water vapor permeability from 4.8 to 25.5 times, while decreasing water absorptiveness from 11.9 to 17.9 times.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "__________ are widely used in paper coatings for oil and moisture resistance in microwave popcorn bags.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorochemicals",
            "b) Hydrogen peroxide",
            "c) Fluorochemicals",
            "d) Polyphenols"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fluorochemicals are widely used in paper coatings for oil and moisture resistance in microwave popcorn bags. It is also used in fast-food paper packaging for muffin and french-fry bags, sandwich/burger wrappers and small pizza and burger boxes. The perfluorocarbon moiety in these classes of products has the effect of lowering the surface energy of the individual paper fibers which greatly contributes to the holdout of low surface energy liquids such as greases and oils.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Pigments comprise ______ of the dry solids in paper coatings.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%–30%",
            "b) 70%–90%",
            "c) 40%–50%",
            "d) 60%–90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The given statement is false. Though functionally and chemically similar, fillers and pigments are distinguished from one another in that fillers are added at the wet end of the paper machine and serve to fill the sheet; pigments are added at the size press and serve to alter the surface of the sheet.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Paper has a definite caused by the greater orientation of fibers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yield",
            "b) Strain",
            "c) Stretch",
            "d) Grain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pigments comprise 70%–90% of the dry solids in paper coatings. They are generally designed to mask or change the appearance of the base stock, improve opacity, impart a smooth and receptive surface for printing or provide special properties for particular purposes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "_________ is made from bleached pulp.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kraft paper",
            "b) Coarse paper",
            "c) Fine paper",
            "d) Glassine paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fine paper is made from bleached pulp. Paper is divided into two broad categories- fine paper and coarse papers. Fine papers are generally used for writing paper, bond, ledger, and book and cover papers. Whereas, coarse papers are generally made of unbleached kraft softwood pulps and are used for packaging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "_________ is a translucent, machine-finished paper which has been hydrated to give oil and grease resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kraft paper",
            "b) Bleach paper",
            "c) Waxed paper",
            "d) Greaseproof paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Greaseproof paper is a translucent, machine-finished paper which has been hydrated to give oil and grease resistance. Prolonged beating or mechanical refining is used to fibrillate and break the cellulose fibers which absorb so much water that they become superficially gelatinized and sticky. This physical phenomenon is called hydration and results in consolidation of the web in the paper machine with many of the interstitial spaces filled in.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following is often used for packaging butter and similar fatty foods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glassine paper",
            "b) Greaseproof paper",
            "c) Vegetable parchment paper",
            "d) Waxed paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Greaseproof paper is often used for packaging butter and similar fatty foods. The satisfactory performance of greaseproof papers depends on the extent to which the pores have been closed. Provided that there are few interconnecting pores between the fibers, the passage of liquids is difficult. However, they are not strictly “greaseproof” because oils and fats will penetrate them after a certain interval of time. Despite this, they are often used for packaging butter and similar fatty foods since they resist the penetration of fat for a reasonable period.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "__________ is typically coarse with exceptional strength.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bleached paper",
            "b) Parchment paper",
            "c) Kraft paper",
            "d) Fine paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Kraft paper is typically coarse with exceptional strength, often made on a Fourdrinier machine and then either machine-glazed on a Yankee dryer or machine-finished on a calender. It is sometimes made with no calendering so that when it is converted into bags, the rough surface will prevent them from sliding over one another when stacked on pallets.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Which of the following paper has excellent wet strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bleached paper",
            "b) Vegetable parchment paper",
            "c) Kraft paper",
            "d) Waxed paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vegetable parchment paper has excellent wet strength. It involves passing a web of high quality, unsized chemical pulp through a bath of concentrated sulfuric acid. The cellulosic fibers swell and partially dissolve, filling the interstices between the fibers and resulting in extensive hydrogen bonding. Thorough washing in water, followed by drying on conventional papermaking dryers, causes reprecipitation and consolidation of the network, resulting in a paper that is stronger wet than dry (it has excellent wet strength, even in boiling water), free of lint, odor and taste, and resistant to grease and oils.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following papers is made from strong sulfite pulp?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kraft paper",
            "b) Waxed paper",
            "c) Vegetable parchment paper",
            "d) Glazed imitation parchment paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glazed imitation parchment (GIP) is made from strong sulfite pulp, which is heavily enginesized and glazed to give the necessary degree of protection. Special finishing processes provide qualities ranging from rough to smooth, brittle to soft and sticky to releasable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "_________ is generally used as an interleaver between slices of food such as meat or pastry.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vegetable parchment paper",
            "b) Kraft paper",
            "c) Bleached paper",
            "d) Waxed paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Because of its grease resistance and wet strength, it strips away easily from food material without defibering, thus finding use as an interleaver between slices of food such as meat or pastry. Labels and inserts in products with high oil or grease content are frequently made from parchment. It can be treated with mold inhibitors and used to wrap foods such as cheese.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "The refractive index of glassine paper is around.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2",
            "b) 2-3",
            "c) 3-4",
            "d) 4-5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The refractive index of glassine paper is around 1-2. Due to the intimate interfiber hydrogen bonding the refractive index of the glassine paper approaches the 1.02 value of amorphous cellulose, indicating that very few pores or other fiber/air interfaces exist for scattering light or allowing liquid penetration. The transparency can vary widely depending on the degree of hydration of the pulp and the basis weight of the paper. The addition of titanium dioxide makes the paper opaque, and it is frequently plasticized to increase its toughness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Waxed papers provide a barrier against _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penetration of oxygen only",
            "b) Penetration of vapors only",
            "c) Penetration of liquids and vapors",
            "d) Penetration of liquids only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Waxed papers provide a barrier against penetration of liquids and vapors. Many base papers are suitable for waxing, including greaseproof and glassine papers. The major types are wet-waxed, dry-waxed and wax-laminated. Wax-sized papers, in which the wax is added at the beater during the papermaking process, have the least amount of wax and therefore give the least amount of protection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "________ is prepared by further treating greaseproof paper in a supercalender.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waterproof paper",
            "b) Machine finished paper",
            "c) Glassine paper",
            "d) Glazed paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Glassine paper is produced by further treating greaseproof paper in a supercalender where is it carefully dampened with water and run through a battery of steam-heated rollers. It derives its name from its glassy, smooth surface, high density and transparency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Iron acts as _______ scavenger system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen",
            "b) carbon dioxide",
            "c) ethylene",
            "d) moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. In Active Packaging, the atmosphere inside the package keeps changing. This type of packaging usually involves an interaction between the packaging components and the food product beyond the inert passive barrier function of the packaging material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "________ enzyme acts as an oxygen scavenging system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) lipase",
            "b) catalase",
            "c) kinase",
            "d) amylase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Intelligent Packaging systems monitor the condition of the packaged foods to give information about the quality of the packaged food during transport and storage. Whereas, active packaging changes the condition of the packed food to extend shelf-life or to improve safety or sensory properties, while maintaining the quality of the packaged food.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Ca(OH)2 and NaOH acts as _______ scavenging system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen",
            "b) carbon Dioxide",
            "c) ethylene",
            "d) moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Iron acts as oxygen scavenger system. 1 gram Iron can absorb upto 300 mL O2. Within 36 hours, Oxygen levels falls down to zero. The disadvantage of this system is that it will not pass through metal detector.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Potassium permanganate acts as _______ scavenging system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen",
            "b) carbon dioxide",
            "c) ethylene",
            "d) moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Catalase enzyme acts as an oxygen scavenging system. It prevents mould, yeast and aerobic bacteria growth and also prevents oxidation of fats, oils, vitamins and preserves the color.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Polyacrylates (sheets), propylene glycol (film), silica gel (sachet) acts as _______ scavenging system.",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen",
            "b) carbon dioxide",
            "c) ethylene",
            "d) moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ca(OH)2 and NaOH acts as carbon dioxide scavenging system. Potassium hydroxide, calcium oxide and silica gel also serves as CO2 scavengers. It is generally used in dehydrated poultry products, roasted coffee, beef jerky, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "_______ is used as a preservative in active packaging.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isoamyl acetate",
            "b) Niacin",
            "c) Ethylene",
            "d) Ethanol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is true. It is generally used in vegetables and fruits, fish, meat, poultry, to inhibit growth of gram-negative bacteria and moulds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "____________ is a common example of an odor absorber.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethene",
            "b) Peroxidase",
            "c) Cyclodextrin",
            "d) Dextrin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Potassium permanganate acts as ethylene scavenging system. It is the most common agent of ethylene removal, which oxidizes ethylene to acetate and ethanol. Ethylene is a natural plant hormone produced by ripening produce. It accelerates respiration, resulting in maturity and senescence. Removing ethylene from a package environment helps extend the shelf life of fresh produce.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "CaO (quicklime) is an example of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ethylene scavengers",
            "b) moisture absorbers",
            "c) flavor and odor absorbers",
            "d) temperature-controlled packages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polyacrylates (sheets), propylene glycol (film), silica gel (sachet) acts as moisture scavenging system. Lower the water activity of the product, lower is the microbial growth. This system consists of a super absorbent polymer located between two layers of a micro-porous or non-woven polymer. This results in enhanced product appearance and freshness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Films containing BHT is an example of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) antioxidant releaser",
            "b) CO2 releaser",
            "c) flavour enhancer",
            "d) aroma enhancer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ethanol is used as a preservative in active packaging.  At high concentration, ethanol denatures the protein of mould and yeast. It can be used by spraying ethanol/water mixture absorbed onto silicon dioxide powder generating ethanol vapors. It is generally used for higher moisture bakery & fish products. Its disadvantage includes- off odour & off flavor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Inner/outer layer of packaging material containing Imazalil is ________ emitters.",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbon dioxide",
            "b) ethylene",
            "c) pesticide",
            "d) oxidant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cyclodextrin is a common example of an odor absorber. Undesirable flavor scalping by the packaging material can result in the loss of desirable food flavors, while foods can pick up undesirable odors or flavors from the package or the surrounding environment.  Cyclodextrin is grafted to a PE layer to absorb accumulated odor from food decomposition.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Silver ion-based film is an example of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen scavenger",
            "b) antimicrobial agent releaser",
            "c) carbon dioxide emitter",
            "d) carbon dioxide adsorbent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CaO (quicklime) is an example of temperature-controlled packages. Temperature-controlled active packages generally include self-heating and self-cooling systems. An exothermic chemical reaction between CaO (quicklime) and a water based solution generates heat. Self- heating packages are commercially available for coffee, tea, and ready-to-eat meals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": " ______ is the most widely used inert gases in MAP.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xenon",
            "b) Krypton",
            "c) Argon",
            "d) Helium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. MAP and CAP are different packaging techniques. Modified atmosphere packaging (MAP) modifies the internal atmosphere inside the packaging using inert gases along with the primary gases, whereas, Controlled Atmosphere Packaging (CAP) regularly regulated the internal atmosphere of the package using primary gases only.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most soluble gas used in MAP?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon Dioxide",
            "b) Nitrogen",
            "c) Oxygen",
            "d) Argon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Modified atmosphere packaging (MAP) is the packaging of a product (perishable) in a modified atmosphere, such that its composition is other than that of air. Therefore elongating shelf life of the product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "_______ employs a continuous gas stream that flushes air out from the package prior to sealing.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermal sealing",
            "b) Gas flushing",
            "c) Thermal flushing",
            "d) Pressure sealing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Controlled atmosphere packaging (CAP) involves maintaining a fixed concentration of gases surrounding the product by careful monitoring and addition of gases. However, the atmosphere inside the package is almost similar to that of air.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Compensated vacuum gas flushing is a ________ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) four-stage",
            "b) three-stage",
            "c) one-stage",
            "d) two-stage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. MAP cannot improve the quality of a poor quality food product. However, it can maintain the quality of the food product and can increase its shelf life from 50-400%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Carbon dioxide is used due to which of its property in food packages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anti-collapse property",
            "b) Filling property",
            "c) Antimicrobial property",
            "d) Ethylene displacing property"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Argon the most widely used inert gases in MAP. It is in commercial use for products such as coffee and snack products. Solubility of Argon decreases with increasing temperature. Its solubility is 100 mg/kg at 0°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a Time-Temperature Indicator (TTI)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Life lines fresh check",
            "b) Radiofrequency identification",
            "c) Electronic nose",
            "d) Ultrasonic indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Intelligent packing can serve as freshness indicator. It can be divided into external and internal indicator on basis of their use. External indicators are those which are attached outside the package. E.g. Time-Temperature & Microbial growth Indicator. Internal indicators are those which are placed inside the package, either to the head space of the package or attached into the lid. Eg. Oxygen Indicators, Carbon dioxide Indicators, Microbial Growth Indicators, Pathogen Indicators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of the following TTI is based on enzymatic lipase color change?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronic nose",
            "b) 3M Monitor Mark",
            "c) LifeLines Fresh-Check",
            "d) Vitsab Single Dot Label (TTI)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Line lines fresh check is a Time-Temperature Indicator (TTI). It is an external indicator, placed outside the food packet. It is generally used in food stored under chilled & frozen conditions. Lifelines’Fresh Check indicators are – color-changing, self-adhesive labels which respond to cumulative exposure to temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Which of the following TTI is based on dye diffusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronic nose",
            "b) 3M Monitor Mark",
            "c) LifeLines Fresh-Check",
            "d) Vitsab Single Dot Label (TTI)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vitsab Single Dot Label (TTI) is based on enzymatic lipase color change. It is based on the principle of enzymatic hydrolysis of a lipid substrate (e.g. tricaproin) causes acid release (e.g. caproic acid) & the pH drop is translated in a color change of pH indicator to dark yellow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Which of the following TTI is based on polymerization reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3M Monitor Mark",
            "b) Electronic nose",
            "c) Vitsab Single Dot Label (TTI)",
            "d) LifeLines Fresh-Check"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 3M Monitor Mark is based on dye diffusion. A  visco-elastic material migrates into a diffusely light reflective porous matrix at a temperature dependent rate. This causes a progressive change of the light transmissivity of the porous matrix & provides a visual response. Response of indicator is the blue dye ester diffusing along a wick. The useful range of temperature & response life of the TTI are determined by type of ester & the concentration at the origin.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an optical chemical sensing method of freshness indication in intelligent packaging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RFID",
            "b) Electronic nose",
            "c) Vitsab Single Dot Label (TTI)",
            "d) 3M Monitor Mark"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LifeLines Fresh-Check is based on polymerization.  It is based on the property of distributed di-acetylene crystals to polymerize through a lattice-controlled solid state reaction proceeding via 1,4 addition polymerization & resulting in high color polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an internal indicator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen indicator",
            "b) Pathogen indicator",
            "c) Microbial growth indicator",
            "d) Time-Temperature indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electronic nose is a simple optical chemical sensing method (colorimetric nose) that utilises the color change taking place in an array of metalloporphyrin dyes upon ligand binding. The liganding vapors (alcohols, amines, ethers, phospines, thiols, halocarbons & ketons) can be visually identified. It is an internal indicator.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Which of the following is based on immuno-chemical methods of freshness indicator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pathogen Indicators",
            "b) Microbial growth indicator",
            "c) Oxygen indicator",
            "d) Carbon dioxide indicator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. RFID: Radio Frequency Identification is a non contact, wireless, data communication form where tags of some material, usually embedded with the IC chip, are programmed with unique information & attach to object for identification & tracking. As tagged items pass by readers, the data from the tags is decoded & transfer to the host computer for processing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "The main component of glass is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) silica",
            "b) quartz",
            "c) sand",
            "d) flint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Glass has been defined by the American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM) as “an amorphous, inorganic product of fusion that has been cooled to a rigid condition without crystallizing”.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "The glass surface is subject to corrosion due to the presence of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) magnesium",
            "b) potassium",
            "c) sodium",
            "d) calcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main component of glass is silica. The principal ingredient of glass is silica derived from sand, flint or quartz. Silica can be melted at very high temperatures (l723°C) to form fused silica glass which, because it has a very high melting point, is used for specialized applications including some laboratory glass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "_______ is characterized by alkaline attack in glass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leaching",
            "b) Etching",
            "c) Scaling",
            "d) Surface bloom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The glass surface is subject to corrosion due to the presence of sodium. The glass surface is subject to three forms of “corrosion”: etching, leaching and weathering, as a consequence of the sodium in glass being loosely combined in the silica matrix.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "What is the basic structural unit of silica in glass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tetrahedron",
            "b) Octahedron",
            "c) Square bipyramidal",
            "d) Trigonal bipyramidal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Etching is characterized by alkaline attack, which slowly destroys the silica network, releasing other glass components. It is a form of corrosion in glass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "________ is characterized by acid attack in glass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weathering",
            "b) Scaling",
            "c) Leaching",
            "d) Surface bloom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The basic structural unit is the silicon oxygen tetrahedron in which a silicon atom is tetrahedrally coordinated to four surrounding oxygen atoms. This amorphous structure, without slip planes formed by crystal boundaries that might allow deformation, is responsible for the stiffness and brittleness of glass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "_______ mild form of weathering in glass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scaling",
            "b) Surface bloom",
            "c) Tempering",
            "d) Leveling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Leaching is characterized by acid attack in which hydrogen ions exchange for alkali or other positively charged mobile ions. The remaining glass (principally silica) usually retains its normal integrity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "______ is the part of the bottle that holds the cap or closure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finish",
            "b) Body",
            "c) Fissure",
            "d) Seal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A mild form of weathering is commonly known as surface bloom and may occur under extended storage conditions. To save the glass from surface bloom, fluorine gas is generally used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "_______ of the container is the portion that is made in the body-mold.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Head",
            "b) Shoulder",
            "c) Cavity",
            "d) Body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Finish is the part of the bottle that holds the cap or closure, the glass surrounding the opening in the container. It includes thread and neck.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Silica is combined with _______ to increase hardness and durability in glass.",
        "Options": [
            "a) boron",
            "b) alumina",
            "c) lead",
            "d) alkali flux"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Body of the container is the portion that is made in the body-mold. Body lies between the finish and the bottom and is generally the largest part of the container. Shoulder is the part between base of neck and the body.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Silica is combined with lead in glass due to which of the following reasons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduce the leaching of sodium",
            "b) Hardness and durability",
            "c) Clarity and brilliance",
            "d) Preventing the glass from dissolving in water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Silica is combined with alumina to increase hardness and durability in glass. Glass contains around 1.5%–2% alumina (Al2O3).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "______ is the spiral groove on the closure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Face",
            "b) Skirt",
            "c) Panel",
            "d) Thread"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silica is combined with lead in glass as lead provides clarity and brilliance to glass. Silica is combined with other raw materials in various proportions for the following reasons-\nAlumina increases hardness and durability.\n6% boron reduces the leaching of sodium.\nCalcium and magnesium carbonates (limestone and dolomite) acts as stabilizers, preventing the glass from dissolving in water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Gasket in glass is also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) liner",
            "b) face",
            "c) thread",
            "d) reverse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thread is the spiral groove on the skirt of a continuous thread closure that meshes with the tread on the glass finish. Face is the outside of the cap. Panel is the flat center area in the top of the closure. Skirt is the flat, almost vertical portion on the side of the closure, which serves as the gripping surface and may be smooth, knurled or fluted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the following is main function of lug-type or twist cap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Closures to retain internal pressure",
            "b) Closures to contain and protect contents",
            "c) Closures to maintain vacuum inside container",
            "d) Closures to secure contents inside containe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gasket or liner is the actual sealing component of the closure, which makes an intimate contact with the glass finish to form an effective seal. Gaskets are made from rubber or plastisols.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following adds rigidity to the cap in glass closure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Curl",
            "b) Face",
            "c) Lug",
            "d) Reverse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Closures used with food containers can be classified under four chidings. They are-\ni. Closures to retain internal pressure – They retain an internal pressure of 200-800 kPa, as found in carbonated drinks and beer. Ex. Crown cork, Roll-on tamper evident aluminum closure\nii. Closures to contain and protect contents – They contain and protect the contents with no internal pressure (Ex. Wine in a bottle). Ex. Bark cork\niii. Closures to maintain vacuum inside container – They maintain a vacuum inside glass containers that typically contain heat-processed food. Ex. Lug-type or twist cap, Press-on twist –off cap, Pry-off (side seal) cap\niv. Closures to secure contents inside container – They are to secure the contents inside the glass container (Ex. Peanut butter).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for the hot and surface treatment of glass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium Oxide",
            "b) Zinc Oxide",
            "c) Tin Oxide",
            "d) Copper Oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tin Oxide is used for the hot and surface treatment of glass. It is an inorganic compound consisting of tin and oxygen. It is commonly used to create customized glass by giving transparent glass an opaque, porcelain-like, opaque appearance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "What are White flints?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lacquered aluminum cans",
            "b) Brown glass",
            "c) Colorless glass",
            "d) Translucent laminates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Standard White flint glass is colorless. White flint glass is defined as a glass of high optical purity and low iron content. Made with the highest quality raw materials, super flint glass is produced using virgin batch materials. This means that more energy is required to melt the materials to the desired quality level.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "A finish is a part of glass bottles where _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) labels are posted",
            "b) cracks can never be formed",
            "c) colors can never be applied",
            "d) closures are applied"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Finish is a part of glass bottles where closures are applied. Finish is the part of the bottle that holds the cap or closure, the glass surrounding the opening in the container.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "Which if the following is used to reduce coloration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CeO2",
            "b) TiO2",
            "c) Na2S",
            "d) Co3O4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The addition of CeO2 (it is reduced to Ce2O3 by the radiations) in glasses in amounts up to 1.5% has proved an effective means of reducing coloration. Unfortunately, it is a very expensive oxide, so glass containers treated this way are significantly more costly than standard containers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to give amber color to glass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CdS + Se",
            "b) Cu2O + CuO",
            "c) NiO",
            "d) Na2S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Na2S is used to give amber color to glass. CdS + Se is used to give orange color to glass. NiO is used to give purple color to glass. Cu2O + CuO is used to give blue color to glass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives black color to glass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MnO",
            "b) CdS",
            "c) Sb2S3",
            "d) Co3O4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Co3O4 (+ Mn, Ni, Fe, Cu, Cr oxides) gives black color to glass. Sb2S3 gives red color to glass. CdS gives yellow color to glass. MnO gives brown color to glass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "_______ glass is the most color sensitive.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yellow",
            "b) Black",
            "c) Flint",
            "d) Amber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The largest constituent (68%–73%) is silica; the second largest constituent (15%–50%) is cullet, originating both as glass scrap from the factory and recycled glass from consumers (so-called postconsumer glass).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The temperature of glass-melting furnace is around ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 800°C",
            "b) 1000°C",
            "c) 1100°C",
            "d) 1500°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flint glass is the most color sensitive with a tolerance of 1% green or 5% amber cullet in the batch mix. Amber glass can tolerate 10% green cullet, while up to a 50% mixture of amber and flint cullet can be used in the production of green glass.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "The process of removal of gases from glass surface is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pressurization",
            "b) refining",
            "c) vaporisation",
            "d) forming"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Cullet also reduces the amount of dust and other particulate matter that often accompanies a batch made exclusively from new raw materials.  The use of cullet is economically desirable since less energy is required to melt cullet than new raw materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Which is the next step after refining in manufacture of glass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blowing",
            "b) Forming",
            "c) Annealing",
            "d) Moulding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The raw materials are weighed, mixed and charged into a glass-melting furnace, which is maintained at a temperature of approximately 1500°C. Here, they are converted into molten glass that is chemically homogeneous and virtually free of gaseous inclusions (bubbles). The melting process consists of two phases: (i) changing the solids into a liquid and (ii) fining or “clearing up” of the liquid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "What is the temperature during the formation of the gob?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1100°C",
            "b) 2000°C",
            "c) 500°C",
            "d) 800°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the refining process, gases (principally CO2, SO2 and water vapor) produced by the chemical reaction rise to the surface of the furnace and are removed. It moves from the furnace into the working end of the furnace (mistakenly called the refiner) where thermal homogenization and cooling of the glass to the viscosity required for the particular operation begin.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The process of converting gob of glass into a bottle or jar is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) threading",
            "b) moulding",
            "c) forming",
            "d) annealing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. During removal of gases, the temperature of melt decreases. The temperature of the melt is lowered from 1250°C to 1350°C to approximately 1100°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Molten glass is also known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) body",
            "b) gob",
            "c) lump",
            "d) mass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The step after refining in manufacture of glass is forming. In this, the molten glass is molded into the desired shape. When the molten glass becomes free of gas (seed-free), it is then ready for forming into containers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "What is the preform before the formation of final glass jar called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mold",
            "b) Gob",
            "c) Tube",
            "d) Parison"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The glass is carried from the working end of the furnace to the forming machine in a channel-like structure called a forehearth, which is fired by a number of small burners, the aim being to ensure uniform temperature distribution throughout the depth of the glass. The glass then passes through a gob-forming mechanism which consists of a rotating sleeve and vertical plunger.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "The pressure temperature combination in formation of glass container is around?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200 kPa, 650°C",
            "b) 100 kPa, 750°C",
            "c) 200 kPa, 500°C",
            "d) 500 kPa, 150°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Precise control of temperature and shape during the formation of the gob is required for the high speed production of accurately formed glass containers. Temperatures in the vicinity of 1100°C varying by no more than ±1°C are typical.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods is used for manufacture of lightweight bottles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Screw press and blow",
            "b) Blow and blow",
            "c) Narrow neck press and blow",
            "d) Neck blow and press"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process of converting a cylindrically shaped gob of glass into a bottle or jar is called forming, and it is essentially a controlled cooling process. While various types of forming machines are used throughout the world, the most predominant type is the IS machine. As its name implies, it consists of up to 16 sections, each one an individually functioning, hollow glass machine. It performs two basic functions: it shapes the gob into a hollow container, and simultaneously removes heat from the gob to prevent it from deforming significantly under its own weight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "The gob is transferred to ___________ after moulding.",
        "Options": [
            "a) roller",
            "b) plunger",
            "c) former",
            "d) annealing lehr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The glass exits in a continuous, viscous stream which is cut by rapidly moving, horizontal steel blades to form what is known as a “gob” (i.e., a mass or lump of molten glass).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "The temperature during annealing is around ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250°C",
            "b) 340°C",
            "c) 540°C",
            "d) 640°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. The containers, from the molder, are transferred from the deadplate to a large oven, known as a lehr, which is equipped with a belt conveyer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "The temperature at which annealing is done is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) melting point",
            "b) softening point",
            "c) transition point",
            "d) gradient point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: This is achieved by raising the temperature of the container to approximately 540°C, holding it there for a few minutes and then cooling at a rate which is consistent with the removal of stress from a predetermined wall thickness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Narrow-neck glass containers are formed by _______ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) blow and press",
            "b) press and press",
            "c) press and blow",
            "d) blow and blow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The temperature at which annealing is done is known as softening point of glass. It melts and reforms glass so that any cracks or deformity can be healed or removed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Wide-mouth glass containers are formed by _______ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) blow and press",
            "b) press and blow",
            "c) blow and blow",
            "d) press and press"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. The function of the annealing lehr is to produce a stable product by removing any residual stresses resulting from non-uniform cooling rates during forming and handling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Wide mouth press and blow process for glass container manufacture does not include which of the following steps?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blank press",
            "b) Neck formation",
            "c) Final shape blown",
            "d) Plunging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. During cooling, the inside surface is hotter than the outside; this results in compression on the outer surface but tension at the inner surface. Sudden cooling results tensile stresses into the outer surfaces and compressional stresses in the interior surfaces. Poor annealing may result in breaking or cracking if interior is bruised or tension is high.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "What enables the glassmaker to decide exactly how the glass is distributed in the parison?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density of gob and plunger",
            "b) Mass of gob and plunger",
            "c) Volume of gob and plunger",
            "d) Temperature of gob and plunger"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Due to the better thickness distribution of lightweight glass bottles, they withstand a maximum temperature difference (progressive thermal shock) of 5°C–10°C higher than the regular weight bottles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What accounts for greater impact strength of lightweight bottles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uniform distribution of weight",
            "b) Uniform distribution of pressure",
            "c) Uniform distribution of volume",
            "d) Uniform distribution of density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Narrow-neck glass containers (bottles) are formed by blow and blow process. Bottles are made by a two step Blow & Blow process, in which a gob of glass is sent to a cast iron mold. The cast iron mold is externally air cooled and hence changes gob to a perform (also known as a parison or body blank).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Temperature of hot-end treatment is glass is around ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300°C",
            "b) 450°C",
            "c) 250°C",
            "d) 550°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In hot-end treatment (typically carried out while the glass container is at 550°C), vapor containing tin or titanium (generally in the form of a tetrachloride) is brought into contact with the outside of the container, forming a thin unimolecular film of metal oxide.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Why is hot-end treatment is done in glass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To prevent surface damage",
            "b) To ensure better adhesion and",
            "c) To strenghthen the surface",
            "d) To prevent surface damage, ensure better adhesion and strenghthen the surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hot-end treatment is done in glass to prevent surface damage. This treatment is done while the container is still hot, strengthens the surface and improves the adhesion of the subsequent cold-end coating.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Temperature of cold-end treatment is glass is around ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200°C",
            "b) 150°C",
            "c) 100°C",
            "d) 80°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cold-end treatment (typically carried out while the glass container is at less than 100°C) is designed to protect the container surface and assist its flow through the filling line.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "What are shrink sleeves in glass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adhesives",
            "b) Temperature control",
            "c) Protective labels",
            "d) Lubricants"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Typically, it involves spraying an organic material in an aqueous base containing either waxes, stearates, silicones, oleic acid or polyethylene onto the outside of the container to increase its lubricity by providing a surface with a low coefficient of friction. It is important to check the compatibility of the cold-end treatment with any adhesives used to attach labels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a cold-end coating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Waxes",
            "b) Polyvinyl alcohol",
            "c) Silicon",
            "d) Nylon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. The function of hot-end treatment and cold-heat treatment in glass is the different. Hot-end treatment is done primarily to prevent surface damage like blurring, whereas, cold-heat treatment is done to increase the lubricity of the surface for better adesion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a hot-end coating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tin chloride",
            "b) Sodium hydroxide",
            "c) Lithium aluminium hydride",
            "d) Boron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Shrink sleeves are protective sheets used on glass. Most shrink sleeves are made of oriented plastic films that shrink around a glass container when heat is applied. Two types of protective labels are used on glass bottles in the form of a body sleeve: one constructed from thin, foamed PS; the other is made from uniaxially oriented PVC or PS. PVC offers  some thermal insulation. Whereas PS contains the glass fragments and prevents shattering of glass, if droppped.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "The term “birdswings” and “spikes” used in glass refers to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) cold-treatment",
            "b) heating oven",
            "c) heat treatment",
            "d) defects."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Hot-end coatings are applied before the container enters the annealing oven (when the glass is still hot due to the previous forming process).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which of the following metal is not used in food packaging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminum",
            "b) Iron",
            "c) Tin",
            "d) Chromium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Iron is not used in food packaging. Iron has greater chances of rusting. For food packaging, four types of metal are commonly used: steel, aluminum, tin, and chromium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "________ is used as protective layer for steel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromium",
            "b) Aluminum",
            "c) Boron",
            "d) Iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Steel and aluminum are commonly used in production of food cans, and are the primary materials for metal packaging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "A metal can is a ________ package.",
        "Options": [
            "a) primary",
            "b) secondary",
            "c) tertiary",
            "d) quaternary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Food cans are most often made of steel, and beverage cans are usually produced from aluminum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "__________ is added to aluminum to improve strength of the alloy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Titanium",
            "b) Chromium",
            "c) Magnesium",
            "d) Tin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Steel tends to oxidize when it is exposed to moisture and oxygen, producing rust. Therefore, chromium is used as protective layers for steel. If chromium is used to provide corrosion protection, the resulting material is called electrolytic chromium- coated steel (ECCS) or tin-free steel (TFS). ECCS has better heat resistance than tinplate and is less expensive.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "The aluminum-copper alloys typically contain between ______% copper.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15-30",
            "b) 15-20",
            "c) 10-20",
            "d) 2-10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Tin is used as protective layers for steel. Tinplate is a composite of tin and steel made by electrolytic coating of bare steel with a thin layer of tin to minimize corrosion. Tinplate is more resistant to corrosion than electrolytic chromium- coated steel (ECCS).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "_______ increases susceptibility of the alloys to Stress corrosion cracking.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silicon",
            "b) Lead",
            "c) Iron",
            "d) Zinc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A metal can is a primary package. The package which is in direct contact with the contained product, providing initial and most crucial protective barrier is known as a primary package. Its main function is containment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "Chromium is added to aluminum alloy to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) prevent recrystallisation",
            "b) increase impact strength",
            "c) increase abrasion resistance",
            "d) prevent cracking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Magnesium is added to aluminum to improve strength. It also increases its strain hardening ability.  These alloys are the highest strength non heat-treatable aluminum alloys and hence are used widely for structural applications.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "______ is added to aluminum alloys to reduce the coefficient of expansion.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zinc",
            "b) Chromium",
            "c) Nickel",
            "d) Manganese"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The aluminum-copper alloy contains between 2-10 % copper. Copper helps in the strength and stability of the alloy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "________ is added to aluminum alloys to increase Young’s modulus.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromium",
            "b) Magnesium",
            "c) Boron",
            "d) Lithium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Copper increases tensile strength, fatigue strength and hardness of the alloys due to the effect of solid solution hardening. It helps to strengthen the alloys by precipitation hardening heat treatment. It decreases the ductility and corrosion resistance of the alloys.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Addition of ______ to aluminum improves fluidity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) vanadium",
            "b) silicon",
            "c) manganese",
            "d) copper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Zinc increases susceptibility of the alloys to Stress corrosion cracking. But addition of zinc to aluminum has some benefits. Zinc, in aluminum alloy increases strength and allows precipitation hardening. Zinc and aluminum alloy is heat-treatable and has a very high strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "The thickness of a tinplate sheet is around ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5–1.5 mm",
            "b) 0.15–0.5 cm",
            "c) 0.5–1.5 cm",
            "d) 0.15–0.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The term tinplate refers to low-carbon, mild steel sheet varying in thickness from around 0.15–0.5 mm with a coating of tin between 2.8 and 17 gsm (g m−2) (0.4–2.5 μm thick) on each surface of the material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "The temperature at which iron ore is heated is around ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2500°C",
            "b) 1000°C",
            "c) 1200°C",
            "d) 1800°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The combination of tin and steel imparts properties – good strength with excellent fabrication qualities like ductility and drawability, weldability, lubricity, lacquerability, non-toxicity and provides corrosion-resistance. Tin and steel together can undergo extensive deformation without fracture.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "The melting point of metallic ores is around ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000°C",
            "b) 1200°C",
            "c) 1800°C",
            "d) 800°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The iron ores used are generally hematite (Fe2O3) with some magnetite (Fe3O4). Commercial extraction of iron from its ores is carried out in blast furnaces, where a mixture of iron ores, solid fuel (coke) and fluxes (limestone and dolomite) are heated to around 1800°C. This results in the reduction of most of the iron oxides to metallic iron (m.p. ≈ 1200°C). Today, modern blast furnaces are capable of producing molten iron of near constant composition at high rates.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Pig iron from blast furnace contains ________ carbon.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5%–2.0%",
            "b) 2.5%–6.0%",
            "c) 6.5%–8.0%",
            "d) 3.5%–5.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. In tinplate, steel serves as the base material. The tin coating adheres sufficiently to the steel base so that it will withstand any degree of deformation that the steel is able to withstand without flaking.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Pig iron from blast furnace contains ________ silicon.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5%–3.0%",
            "b) 0.3%–1.0%",
            "c) 1.5%–2.0%",
            "d) 0.1%–0.5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The melting point of metallic ores is around 1200°C. Iron ores are generally heated at 1800°C, so that it reduces to metallic ores.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "Pig iron from blast furnace contains ________ manganese.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) 1%",
            "d) 2.5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pig iron from a blast furnace contains 3.5%–5.0% carbon.  Carbon is the most important alloying element for steel and affects the strength of cans. Carbon in higher concentration, when combined with manganese results in higher steel strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Pig iron from blast furnace contains ________ phosphorous.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5%",
            "b) 1%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 3%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pig iron from blast furnace contains 0.3%–1.0% silicon. Hardness of pig iron decreases with increase in silicon. But, addition of a little amount of silicon improves the microstructure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Pig iron from blast furnace contains ________ sulfur.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1%",
            "b) 0.5%",
            "c) 0.08%",
            "d) 0.8%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pig iron from blast furnace contains up to 2.5% manganese. Manganese greatly contributes to increasing the hardness of the pig iron.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "The thickness of iron slabs after rolling is around _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 550 mm",
            "b) 150 mm",
            "c) 100 mm",
            "d) 250 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pig iron from blast furnace contains 1% phosphorous. Phosphorus generally contributes to the increase in eutectic temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "The process of scale removal in manufacture tinplate is known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) pickling",
            "b) leaching",
            "c) flaming",
            "d) charring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pig iron from blast furnace contains 0.08% sulfur. The low concentration of sulfur increases longevity. But a higher concentration acts as an impurity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "The final stage of thickness reduction is carried out by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) roll pressing",
            "b) screw pressing",
            "c) hot rolling",
            "d) cold rolling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: These metalloids must be substantially reduced in the steelmaking stage, and this is commonly accomplished using a basic oxygen furnace. From the furnace, the steel is cast into ingots, which are subsequently rolled into slabs about 250 mm thick or, more commonly today, continuously cast into slab form.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "_______ is used for removing scales during the manufacture of tinplate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lithium hydride",
            "b) Hydroboric acid",
            "c) Orthophosphoric acid",
            "d) Hydrochloric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of scale removal in manufacture tinplate is known as pickling. The thick slabs are hot rolled down to about 2 mm and, during this process, substantial layers (0.01 mm thick) of oxides or scale are formed as a consequence of the steel being heated to elevated temperatures for rolling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an iron ore?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hematite",
            "b) Magnetite",
            "c) Cryolite",
            "d) Limonite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cryolite (Na3AlF6, sodium hexafluoroaluminate) is an aluminum ore. Hematite (Fe2O3), Siderite (FeCO3), Magnetite (Fe3O4) and Limonite (FeO•nH2O) are iron ores.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "_________ is the process after cold rolling.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pickling",
            "b) Annealing",
            "c) Tempering",
            "d) Milching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Annealing is the process after cold rolling. In the process of annealing the steel is heated to temperatures of 600°C 700°C to relieve the stresses from the rolling process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Temper rolled steel is also known as ________ reduced.",
        "Options": [
            "a) single",
            "b) double",
            "c) triple",
            "d) seam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Annealing removes stress by mildly increasing the temperature. Annealing results in recrystallization of the elongated ferrite grains into new fine grains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Cold rolled steel is also known as ________ reduced.",
        "Options": [
            "a) single",
            "b) double",
            "c) triple",
            "d) seam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Annealing takes place after cold rolling. Two different annealing processes are used after cold rolling: continuous annealing (which results in a strong material with a fine grain structure) and batch annealing (which has a coarse grain structure but excellent formability).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "The minimum thickness for single reduced steel is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.16 mm",
            "b) 0.12 mm",
            "c) 0.18 mm",
            "d) 0.10 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Temper rolled steel is also known as single reduced. Temper rolling imparts springiness to the steel. Temper rolling is done after annealing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "The minimum thickness for double reduced steel is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.16 mm",
            "b) 0.12 mm",
            "c) 0.18 mm",
            "d) 0.10 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cold rolled steel is also known as double reduced. Double reduced (DR) material is very strong and stiff and has a higher hardness for a given thickness, allowing the use of comparatively thin gauges for many applications. However, it has only limited forming possibilities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Lankford coefficient is a measure of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bendiness",
            "b) graininess",
            "c) plastic anisotropy",
            "d) crystallinilty"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Minimum thickness for double reduced steel is 0.18 mm for single reduced (SR) plate. Temper rolled steel is also known as single reduced.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "The uncoated steel sheet before tinplating is known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) steelplate",
            "b) bareplate",
            "c) blackplate",
            "d) foreplate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The uncoated steel sheet before tinplating is referred to as blackplate, thus called because some of the early production was covered with black iron oxide. It is the raw material for electrolytic tinplate (ETP) and ECCS.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "________ refers to an arbitrary number designation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Etxruding",
            "b) Polishing",
            "c) Rolling",
            "d) Temper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. To reduce the possibility of severe fluting, paneling or creasing, and to impart the desired surface finish, the steel is given a final, very light cold rolling (generally a reduction of less than or equal to 5.0% in thickness) in a Temper mill.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Blackplate has _______ coating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) chromium oxide",
            "b) aluminum oxide",
            "c) iron oxide",
            "d) zinc oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Temper refers to an arbitrary number designation. This designation is the summation of several mechanical properties such as elasticity, springiness, stiffness and fluting tendency and therefore gives information about the forming properties of tin mill products..\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Type of steel in tinplate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) P",
            "b) N",
            "c) L",
            "d) D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blackplate has iron oxide coating. At this stage, the uncoated steel sheet is referred to as blackplate, thus called because some of the early production was covered with black iron oxide. It is the raw material for electrolytic tinplate (ETP) and ECCS.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Steel of type ____ is used where high internal corrosion resistance is required.",
        "Options": [
            "a) D",
            "b) L",
            "c) MR",
            "d) N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The Rockwell hardness test has been adopted as the industry standard to express temper because of its simplicity and overall good correlation with fabrication requirements. This test is done with a 30kg load attached to a 1.6 mm diameter ball. The load is introduced into the plate surface. The measurement is taken and expressed as Rockwell 30T reading, which can be converted to temper values using arbitrary scale.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Steel of type ___ is used in can ends.",
        "Options": [
            "a) D",
            "b) L",
            "c) MR",
            "d) N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are four types of steel used in tinplate- D, L, N and MR. Steel D is used for drawing operations. Steel L is used for corrosion resistance. Steel N is nitrogenised steel. Steel MR is the most widely used tinplate steel used in the food industry.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Steel type ___ is used for tinplates for packing vegetable and meat packs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) D",
            "b) L",
            "c) MR",
            "d) N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Steel of type L is used where high internal corrosion resistance is required. Its properties include- high purity; low in residual elements.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Steel type ___ is used for tinplates in D&I cans.",
        "Options": [
            "a) D",
            "b) L",
            "c) MR",
            "d) N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Steel of type N is used where high strength and rigidity required (e.g. can ends). Steel of type N is nitrogenized steel with up to 0.02% N to increase strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "The method of making tinplate by electroplating is also known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) selective tinplating",
            "b) uniform tinplating",
            "c) bilayer tinplating",
            "d) differential tinplating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Higher strength steels are suitable for welded food cans, while softer, more formable grades are better for drawn cans and components such as aerosol tops and bottoms, fish or beverage cans.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "The melting point of tin is around ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 190°C–200°C",
            "b) 260°C–270°C",
            "c) 350°C–360°C",
            "d) 200°C–210°C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Tinplating is the method of depositing tin on steel. The quality or type of steel used depends on the purpose for which tinplate will be used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "During tinplating _______ is formed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) FeCl2",
            "b) SnCl2",
            "c) FeSn2",
            "d) SnO2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The method of making tinplate by electroplating is also known as differential tinplating. The introduction of the electroplating process enabled a different thickness of tin to be applied to the two surfaces of the steel. Differential tinplating is the most cost-effective method and is efficient in covering interior and exterior of the container in a single step.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "_______ is the final step in tinplating.",
        "Options": [
            "a) De-oiling",
            "b) Activating",
            "c) Passivating",
            "d) Oiling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Acid stannous sulfate process is generally known as the Ferrostan process. It is preceded by cleaning in a pickling and degreasing unit, followed by thorough washing to prepare the surface. Following which the coating is passivated and is flow melted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "The oil film weights are generally in the range of_______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5–10 mg m-2",
            "b) 1–5 mg m-2",
            "c) 10–15 mg m-2",
            "d) 1–5 mg m-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. In this method, plating is done via electroplating using halogen gas. Using halogen in tinplating has additional benefits as it increases the stability. Also, halogen in the process can be recycled and reused.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Filling of sterile containers with commercially sterile product is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) passive packaging",
            "b) active packaging",
            "c) intelligent packaging",
            "d) aseptic packaging"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Filling of sterile containers with commercially sterile product is known as aseptic packaging. ‘Asepsis’ means exclusion or absence of any unwanted microorganism. Aseptic packaging is done-\ni.\tto take advantage of HTST sterilization process.\nii.\tto enable containers to be used that are unsuitable for in-package sterilization\niii.\tto extend the shelf life of product at normal temperature by packaging them aseptically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "The sealing in aseptic packaging is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vacuum sealing",
            "b) hermetic sealing",
            "c) closed sealing",
            "d) thermo sealing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sealing in aseptic packaging is known as hermetic sealing. Hermetic sealing is done to prevent recontamination of enclosed product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which of the following steps is not included in aseptic packaging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sterilizing product before filling",
            "b) Hermetic Sealing",
            "c) Aseptic filling",
            "d) Sterilizing product after filling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The given statement is false. In-package sterilization is the process in which the package is sterilized after filling. Whereas, in aseptic packaging sterilized product is filled in sterilized container in a controlled environment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "The first aseptic packaging of food was carried out in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1913",
            "b) 1926",
            "c) 1950",
            "d) 1974"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sterilizing product after filling is not included in aseptic filling. Aseptic packaging contains the following steps –\ni)\tSterilizing product before filling\nii)\tSimultaneous sterilizing package before filling\niii)\tFilling in aseptic environment\niv)\tHermetic sealing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "___________ process is used in aseptic packaging.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autoclaving",
            "b) Sterilization",
            "c) Disinfection",
            "d) Heating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first aseptic packaging of food was carried out in 1913. Nielsen from Denmark aseptically packaged milk in metal cans.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Sterilization using irradiation is done by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-ionizing radiation",
            "b) Ionizing radiation",
            "c) Chemical Treatment",
            "d) Thermal Treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sterilization process is used in aseptic packaging. Sterilization is the process of removal or destruction of all microbial life. There are three common sterilization processes –LTLT, HTST and UHT.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for ionizing radiation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infrared radiation",
            "b) Microwave radiation",
            "c) Radiowave radiation",
            "d) Gamma radiation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. LTLT stands for Low Temperature Long Time Sterilization. LTLT process includes heating the product at low temperature for a longer time (LTLT – 63.15°C, 30 minute). This long time process makes it very slow. Therefore it is not used in aseptic packaging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a chemical used in aseptic packaging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorine peroxide",
            "b) Lithium oxide",
            "c) Hydrogen Peroxide",
            "d) Hydrogen Sulfide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. UHT stands for Ultra High Temperature. UHT process includes heating the product at ultra high temperature for a very short span of time (UHT – 75°C to 140°C, less than 5 seconds). This process is very efficient due to the short time it consumes. Therefore, it is very favorably used in aseptic packaging.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for checking integrity of aseptic packaging material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sterility test",
            "b) Drop test",
            "c) Bursting test",
            "d) Grammage test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. HTST stands for High Temperature Short Time. HTST process includes heating the product at high temperature for a short time (HTST – 72° C, 15 minutes).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to pack carbonated soft drinks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDPE",
            "b) PET",
            "c) PS",
            "d) PVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PET – Polyethylene Terephthalate is widely used to pack carbonated soft drinks. The PET bottle is usually fitted with either a standard aluminium roll-on closure or a pre-threaded plastic cap, both either in the standard or pilfer-proof form.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to pack fried snack foods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) LDPE",
            "b) PET",
            "c) PS",
            "d) PVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: LDPE- Low Density Polyethylene is widely used to pack fried foods. Paperboard cans lined with a barrier polymer such as aluminium foil is sealed with LDPE-foil end.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to pack coffee?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PET & LDPE",
            "b) HDPE",
            "c) HDPE & PS",
            "d) PET & PVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Metalized PET laminated to LDPE is frequently used to pack coffee. This layer of polymer prevents staling and loss of flavor volatiles or chemical changes in the volatile components caused by moisture and O2 absorption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for packaging of milk in pouches?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyvinyl",
            "b) Polyethylene Terephthalate",
            "c) Polyethylene",
            "d) Polyester"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polyester pouches are used for packaging milk. Packaging materials used for milk should ideally not transmit more than 8% of incident light at 500nm wavelength and not more than 2% at 400nm wavelength. Other materials used for the same include – polypropylene, polystyrene, poly vinyl chloride, polyvinyldiene chloride (cryovac), rubber hydrochloride (pliofilm), polyester, polyamide (nylon), saran (a mixed polymer).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is used in packaging yoghurt in cups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low Density Polyethylene",
            "b) Polystyrene",
            "c) Polyvinyl Chloride",
            "d) High density Polyethylene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polystyrene cups are used in packaging yoghurt. Other than yoghurt, it is also used in packaging ice-creams. Amongst all varieties of Polystyrene, thermoformed HIPS(High Impact Polystyrene) in the form of small cups or larger tubs, with either an aluminum foil/plastic laminate or a paper/plastic laminate heat seal lid or closure is used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for primary packaging of butter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oiled Paper",
            "b) Kraft Paper",
            "c) Wax Paper",
            "d) Parchment Paper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vegetable parchment is the primary packaging used in butter. The main control points in the packaging of butter include- oxidation, water permeability and vapor permeability. Aluminum foil (0.009 mm thick) laminated either to 40 gsm greaseproof paper or vegetable parchment. Other types of packaging include plastic tubs thermoformed from white-pigmented HIPS or PVC with a tight-fitting lid of the same material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is used as a primary package in biscuits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PE",
            "b) LDPE",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) BOPP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: BOPP (bioriented polypropylene) filmis used as a primary package in biscuits. For higher quality products, duplex OPP or OPP combinations such as OPP/PE, OPP/PET, OPP/PVdC in the appropriate thickness and sealing range are used. It offers effective barrier against gas, odor and light. The plastic polyfilm is used in combination with an inner aluminium layer of approximately 7 microns.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following material is used as a primary package in bread?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDPE",
            "b) LDPE",
            "c) PS",
            "d) PVC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LDPE (Low Density Polyethylene) is used as a primary package in bread. The LDPE bag is sealed with PS tag. Vacuum packaging is not sustainable as crushing could take place. Gas mixture in the packaging usually ranges from 100% CO2 to 50:50 CO2:N2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the abrasion resistance layer in a retort pouch?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polypropylene",
            "b) Nylon",
            "c) Aluminum Foil",
            "d) Polyester"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nylon is the abrasion resistance layer in a retort pouch. Propylene is the physical food contact layer (primary package). It is a heat seal surface and provides flexibility.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following polymer is used as a printing surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polypropylene",
            "b) Nylon",
            "c) Aluminum Foil",
            "d) Polyester"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polyester is the printable surface as well as the outermost layer in a retort pouch. It also provides strength.  Aluminum foil is the barrier layer of a retort. It protects from light, gases and odors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Tetrapak has _______ layers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tetrapak has 6 layers. The innermost to outermost layers are –\ni)\tPolyethylene (innermost)\nii)\tPaper\niii)\tPolyethylene\niv)\tAluminium\nv)\tPolyethylene\nvi)\tPolyethylene (outermost).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "What is the function of Polyethylene in Tetrapak?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical rigidity",
            "b) Gas barrier",
            "c) Abrasion resistance",
            "d) Liquid barrier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polyethylene serves multiple functions in Tetrapak (paperboard carton). The innermost layer is used as a liquid barrier and to bind layers of aluminum, primary layer, paper, printing layer together.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which is the thinnest layer in Tetrapak?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyethylene",
            "b) Paper",
            "c) Nylon",
            "d) Aluminium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Aluminium foil is the thinnest layer in Tetrapak(paperboard carton). It is around 7 microns in width. Aluminium provides the best gas barrier and prevents exposure to sunlight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which is the thickest layer in Tetrapak?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyethylene",
            "b) Paper",
            "c) Nylon",
            "d) Aluminium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Paper is the thickest layer in Tetrapak. Tetrapak is also known as paperboard carton because of the same. Paper is bound to other layers by polyethylene.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The headspace maintained in wine bottles is around _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10mm",
            "b) 20mm",
            "c) 15mm",
            "d) 25mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The headspace maintained in wine bottles is around 15mm. Headspace is the space between cap of the bottle and the food product. Headspace is essential to avoid spilling while opening.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The filler gas used in wine cans is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) O2",
            "b) He",
            "c) CO2",
            "d) N2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Wine should always be packed in colored or tinted glass bottles (generally dark green/ brown). Exposure to sunlight makes it more susceptible to oxidation, hence resulting in a dull, flat, oxidized flavor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for microwave ovenable trays?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PVC",
            "b) HDPE",
            "c) PET",
            "d) PS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The filler gas used in wine cans is N2. It is necessary to increase the internal pressure in the cans to prevent collapse. Internal pressure is approximately 170kPa.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Which of the following plastic polymer is used for chips packaging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PVDC",
            "b) PP",
            "c) PE",
            "d) LDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Wine can be packed in a fiberboard box, which is laminated (internally) by PVdC copolymer-coated PA-LDPE laminate. It is also known as a Bag-in-Box (BIB) package.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following plastic polymers is used for packaging of fresh produce?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dextrose",
            "b) PS",
            "c) PVdC",
            "d) LDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PET (Polyethylene Terephthalate) is used for microwave ovenable trays. It is also used for “boil‐in‐the‐bag” products which are frozen before use. It has a oriented crystalline structure (35-45% crystallinity), making it stable upto 140-160°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Purple staining is related to a defect in which packaging?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PET bottles",
            "b) Glass bottles",
            "c) Metal cans",
            "d) Paperboard"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PVDC- Polyvinyldiene Chloride has excellent water vapor and gas barrier properties. Not only this, its heat sealing characteristics and resistance to oils & fats makes it an ideal choice to pack chips.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Which of the following is most widely for packaging raw fruits & vegetables?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PVC",
            "b) OPP",
            "c) BOPP",
            "d) LLDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PS – Polystyrene has very high vapor and gas transmission rate – hence, making it a breathable film. However, it is not suitable for heat sterilization and deteriorates on exposure to sunlight. This film is crystal clear and sparkling, enabling consumers to see through it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Which of the following materials is most suitable for the packaging of pre-processed vegetables?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDPE, LLDPE, PVC",
            "b) PVdC, OPP, HDPE",
            "c) OPP, LDPE, LLDPE",
            "d) PS, BOPP, HDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. R-enamel stands for Regular enamel. It includes – phenolic resin or epoxy phenolic coating (resole phenolic) with BPA epoxy and H3PO4 catalyst.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Twist wrapping is used in which of the following products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biscuit",
            "b) Toffees",
            "c) Bread",
            "d) Cookies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Purple staining is observed in metal cans. This defect refers to the blackening of inner side of can. It occurs when sulphur containing food reacts with iron in the can to form purple iron sulphide.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used in packaging whole milk powder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aluminium+ polyethylene",
            "b) Aluminium+ polystyrene",
            "c) Aluminium+ PVC",
            "d) Aluminium+ PET"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Blend of polyolefilms –mainly LLDPE is used for packaging raw fruits & vegetables . Film contains pigments to protect it from sunlight. LLDPE is stretchable and transparent, enabling consumers to look into the packet.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which of the following products can be vacuum packed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cookies",
            "b) Walnuts",
            "c) Crackers",
            "d) Milk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most suitable are polymeric blend of LLDPE, LDPE or OPP with EVA copolymer.\n\n\nVegetable\nPackging material and thickness\n\n\nPeeled potato, both whole and sliced\nLDPE, 50 μm\n\n\nGrated carrot\nOPP, 40 μm, microperforated LDPE-EVA-OPP, 30-40 μm\n\n\nSliced beetroot\nLDPE, 50 μm\n\n\nGrated beetroot\nOPP, 40 μm, microperforated OPP,PE EVA-OPP 30-40 μm\n\n\nShredded white cabbage\nOPP, 40 μm, LDPE-EVA-OPP, 30-40 μm\n\n\nShredded onion\nOPP, 40 μm\n\n\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as C enamel on cans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ZnO",
            "b) PbS",
            "c) NaOH",
            "d) H2S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Twist wrapping is used in packaging of toffees. Twist wrapping includes cutting a piece of packaging film, rolling and forming it to a tube around the object and twisting the ends of the tube.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "In which year was the Food and Drugs act was imposed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1880",
            "b) 1906",
            "c) 1954",
            "d) 1910"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The 1906 Food and Drugs Act was the first time that the U.S. Government exercised the principle that it has a duty to protect public health by controlling the adulteration of food.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the right expansion of GRAS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generally Recognized as Safe",
            "b) Generally Recommended as Safe",
            "c) Globally Recognized as Safe",
            "d) Globally Recommended as Safe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. In 1958, congress passed the Food Additives Amendment to the 1938 Act. Delaney clause states that no additive shall be deemed to be safe if it is found to induce cancer when ingested by man or animal, or if it is found, after tests which are appropriate for the evaluation of the safety of food additives, to induce cancer in man or animal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expansion of SWAMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard Wage and Measure Act",
            "b) Standard Ward and Measure Act",
            "c) Standard Weights and Meter Act",
            "d) Standard Weights and Measures Act"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The term GRAS stands for Generally Recognized as Safe. It includes food ingredients as well as prior-sanctioned food ingredients.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Liquid commodities belong to which class under SWAMA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) C",
            "d) D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SWAMA stands for Standard Weight and Measure Act. This act says that the commodities to be packed for retail should be packed in standard specific quantities as given under the rule for each commodity. The units adopted are the International System of units.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "What is the correct expansion of ASTM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) American Society for Tempering Machines",
            "b) American Society for Testing & Measurements",
            "c) American Standards for Testing of Materials",
            "d) American Society for Testing & Materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The products with net weight or volume less than or equal to 25gm or 25cc fall under Class-A of SWAMA.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "When was Fruit Products Order (FPO) enacted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1937",
            "b) 1974",
            "c) 1955",
            "d) 1951"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Liquid commodities belong to Class-B under SWAMA. All commodities whose flow properties, density or both cannot be maintained constant except with the help of considerable special technical effort, belong to Class-A.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "When was AGMARK enacted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1937",
            "b) 1946",
            "c) 1952",
            "d) 1968"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. The weight of the package is not included in the net weight of the commodity, only if-the total weight of such immediate wrappers does not exceed:\n•\t8%, where wrapper (primary package) is a waxed paper or any other paper, with wax or aluminium foil (under strip), or\n•\t6%, paper (not waxed).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "When was Edible Oil Packaging (Regulation) Order enacted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1984",
            "b) 1954",
            "c) 1951",
            "d) 1998"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: ASTM – American Society for Testing & Materials is an international standards organization formed in 1998 for developing and publishing technical standards for a wide range of materials by voluntary consensus.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "When was Meat Food Products Order enacted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1973",
            "b) 1954",
            "c) 1951",
            "d) 1937"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Fruit Products Order was enacted in 1955. It is concerned with fruit and vegetable products including synthetic beverages, syrups, sharbats and vinegar. The objective of this law is to regulate the quality and hygiene of these products.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "When was Milk and Milk Product Order enacted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1973",
            "b) 1983",
            "c) 1992",
            "d) 1987"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: AGMARK was enacted in 1937. It stands for Agricultural Produce Grading and Marketing Act. It gives a certification mark on agricultural produce in India. It includes all agricultural (raw and semi-processed) commodities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "When was PFA act enacted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1954",
            "b) 1976",
            "c) 1983",
            "d) 1992"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Edible Oil Packaging (Regulation) Order was enacted in 1998. It ensures the availability of safe and quality edible oil in packed form.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expansion of FSSAI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Food Security and Standards Authority of India",
            "b) Food Safety and Security Authority of India",
            "c) Food Safety and Surety Authority of India",
            "d) Food Safety and Standards Authority of India"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: FSSAI stands for Food Safety and Standards Authority of India. It is the apex food safety and regulatory authority in India. It protects and promotes public health through the regulation and supervision of food safety.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "In which year was Food Safety and Standards act enacted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2005",
            "b) 2000",
            "c) 2006",
            "d) 2011"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Food Safety and Standards act was enacted in 2006. It contains 101 sections. Food Safety and Standards Authority of India was established in 2011 under FSS Act.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the appropriate expansion of NABL?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National Accreditation Board for Testing and Calibration of Laboratories",
            "b) National Accreditation Board for Testing and Certification of Laboratories",
            "c) National Accreditation Board for Laboratories",
            "d) National Accreditation Board for Certification of Laboratories"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NABL stands for National Accreditation Board for Testing and Calibration of Laboratories. It is the sole laboratory accreditation authority in India. It was established under the Department of Science and Technology, Government of India. It provides accreditation to testing and calibration of clinical laboratories to assess quality and technical competence of labs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used instead of Expiry-date on packages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Best-before date",
            "b) Use-by date",
            "c) Marketable-by date",
            "d) Marketable-before date"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. BIS (Bureau of Indian Standards) gives Product Specific Certification.  ISO (International Organization for Standardization) gives Process specific certification.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expansion of CAC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cognitive Alimentarius Commission",
            "b) Cognitive Alimentarius Corporation",
            "c) Codex Alimentarius Corporation",
            "d) Codex Alimentarius Commission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Best-before date signifies that the quality of product deteriorates. It is however, safe to consume after the best-before date. Use-by date signifies that the product will not have the similar product quality and safety attributes as before.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expansion of FDA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Food and Drug Affiliation",
            "b) Food and Drug Administration",
            "c) Food and Drug Abuse",
            "d) Food and Drug Authority"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Expiry date is also known as Use-by date. This signifies the last day after which the product should not be consumed owing to deteriorating safety of the product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct expansion of BIS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Branch of Indian Standards",
            "b) Bureau for Investigation of Standards",
            "c) Bureau of International Standards",
            "d) Bureau of Indian Standards"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. ‘Health claim’ means any representation that suggests that a relationship exists between a food and health, which include nutrition claims which describe the physiological role of the nutrient in growth, development and normal functions of the body. ‘Nutrition claim’ is a representation which suggests that a food has particular nutritional properties which are not limited to the energy value.\n"
    }
]